<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Behind the Tower</title>
    <description>Behind the Tower: New Histories of the UT Tower Shooting is a public history of the mass shooting that Charles Whitman carried out at UT Austin on August 1, 1966, the collective work of eleven graduate students and one History professor at The University of Texas at Austin.
</description>
    <link>http://behindthetower.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://behindthetower.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 17:46:15 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 17:46:15 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Update July-August, 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In July 2016, the hard to find rock and plaque that honored the victims of August 1, 1966 has been removed and a new monument is being prepared to be unveiled on August 1, 2016, the 50th anniversary. We will post more about the commemoration of that day as more information becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/neuberger/july-2016-update.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of construction around memorial pond&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/neuberger/july-2016-update-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of construction around memorial pond&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/update-july-august-2016</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/update-july-august-2016</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Charles Joseph Whitman (1941-1966)</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;How can we talk about Charles Whitman? How &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; we talk about Charles Whitman?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;floated-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/neuberger/charles-whitman.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Charles Whitman&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Some of his victims and some of the witnesses to his killing rampage don’t even want to say his name. He was a “monster,” a “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/the-madman-on-the-tower/&quot;&gt;madman&lt;/a&gt;,” a murderer and nothing more. In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.towerdocumentary.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tower&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Keith Maitland’s moving 2016 film about the heroism of the victims and survivors, Whitman’s face is never seen. This is a historical shift from the first months and even decades after the shooting, when Charles Whitman was the main focus of attention.  In the early stages, horror and incomprehension prevailed. How could he? Who was he? Governor John Connally convened a special commission, which released a report just 5 weeks later, to try to answer those questions.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;At the time, and even in the days after the tragic shooting, Whitman was described in glowing terms. On August 2, 1966, &lt;em&gt;The Austin American&lt;/em&gt; headlined its front page attempt to construct his biography: “&lt;a href=&quot;/how-austin-newspapers-covered-the-shooting&quot;&gt;’Everyone’ Loved Him&lt;/a&gt;.” Until, that is, he “snapped.”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As Dr. Coleman de Chenar, the pathologist who performed the autopsy on Whitman, said, the shooter was “an anti-social psychopath, and that’s the worst kind.”  He could be be social and friendly and make a good impression, but he concealed deep hostilities.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Life Magazine&lt;/em&gt; also presented Whitman from two sides.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;He was big, strong, handsome, neat, hardworking. He was pleasant to be around and interesting to talk with. He spoke ill of no one – except, occasionally, his father – and he tried to speak well of many people. His grades were excellent. He enjoyed civic work, loved his wife, admired his professors and seemed to have no enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;But he was also a violent man. He bit his nails to the quick and perspired ‘rings of sweat on the coolest days.’ He was a meticulous perfectionist… . What he said in deep intimate conversations changed from person to person.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In the last decades of the 20th century, ironic references to Whitman were the norm. He was the Marine and Eagle Scout  who turned into a mass murderer. As Rosa Eberly noted, his name appears in numerous films, from made-for-tv movies to indie classic, &lt;em&gt;Slacker&lt;/em&gt;, to Stanley Kubrick’s &lt;em&gt;Full Metal Jacket&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But media attention to the increasing number of lone shooter mass murderers has led many observers to believe that the media itself enables copy-cats and leads to more violence by making them famous media stars. This view seems to indicate a belief that such lone mass shooters crave publicity for suicidal stunts; that they are cruel and indifferent narcissists. But the fact is that we still do not know what makes someone carry out a mass attack. This view might also suggest that the shooter’s motives and identity are irrelevant in light of the trauma they caused.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Is curiosity and the desire to understand mass murderers a symptom of the modern media circus?  &lt;br /&gt;
Is empathy only available to people at a distance?   &lt;br /&gt;
Does a need to start paying more attention to the victims and the survivors mean that we have to stop trying to understand the perpetrators?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Charles Whitman suffered abuse as a child, anxiety as an adult, and serious physical and mental illness in the months (and maybe years) before he slaughtered 16 people, wounded 32 others, and traumatized many more.  He sought help from an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/the-madman-on-the-tower/&quot;&gt;unfeeling psychiatrist&lt;/a&gt; for the violent impulses that terrified him.  Should we spare some sympathy for him?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Or, do we talk about how he was an Eagle Scout at age 12? How he excelled in the Marines and received a prestigious scholarship to UT Austin? Do we talk about how he struggled to succeed in life when neither his father nor his superior officers were telling him what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Do we talk about the total lack of “red flags”? Or all the signs of trouble that emerged in the years that followed? The stressful marriage, the stressful college career, the stressful military career, the friends who said Kathy told them that Charlie hit her, the brain tumor, the psychiatrist, the diary where he confessed first his fears and later his most irrational thoughts about killing his wife and mother? Do those experiences explain the man who murdered the women he loved most before becoming the cold-blooded sniper?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;We have gotten no closer to predicting or understanding what makes someone – even someone very troubled, someone suffering from serious physical and mental illness – go out and buy an arsenal of guns and ammunition and go to a public place and start killing people.  The maker of a new film about the Boston Marathon bombers, a childhood friend of one of the murderers, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wbur.org/hereandnow/2016/04/22/jahar-film-kanno-youngs-hayes&quot;&gt;recently said&lt;/a&gt;, “I know it’s hard for people to hear, but this is the hard truth in a way, the fact is there were no red flags. There was nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As historians, we believe that it is our job to study and report on the whole event – perpetrator and victims and eyewitnesses alike. Eleven out of the twelve co-authors of this website found that the more they learned about Whitman’s own struggle, the harder it was to resist some empathy for him. One student, though, found that no matter how much she learned about Whitman, he did not elicit any of her sympathy.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Was Charles Whitman a monster or sufferer? Was he a sociopath or mentally ill, or was his brain deformed by a tumor? Do you want to vilify or sympathize with him?  As we struggle to contain accelerating gun violence in the U.S., at least let our choices be based on research and evidence rather than on prejudice and preconception.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Joan Neuberger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Nat Henderson, “Sniper ‘Worst type’ Psycho.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;David Nevin, “The Eagle Scout Who Grew Up with a Tortured Mind,” &lt;em&gt;Life Magazine&lt;/em&gt;, August 12, 1966, 28D. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rosa A. Eberly, “’Everywhere You Go, It’s There’: Forgetting and Remembering the University of Texas Tower Shootings,” &lt;em&gt;Framing Public Memory&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Kendall R. Phillips (University of Alabama Press, 2004), 72-73. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/charles-joseph-whitman</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/charles-joseph-whitman</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aftermath</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;People always remember where they are when something terrible happens. Everyone can give you their 9/11 memories right now if they were old enough to remember. If you happened to be in Austin, Texas in the summer of 1966, you remember exactly where you were when Charles Whitman acquainted America with the concept of mass murder on a school campus.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;People at The University of Texas at Austin didn’t know how to recover after August 1, when one of their own murdered sixteen fellow Longhorns and other civilians. The silence that surrounded the campus afterwards was deafening. The university was not prepared to handle this type of tragedy. No one even knew how to memorialize the people who lost their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;There were countless students, faculty, visitors, and others on the campus that afternoon when shots began to fire from the tower. Much of the focus since 1966 has been on the shooter, Charles Whitman, and the people he killed. But it is critical to focus on the survivors of that day: How did they live and continue carrying the memories of August 1, 1966? How do these people define themselves? Are they victims? Are they survivors? Eye witnesses?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;After that deadly day, people struggled with remembering or forgetting the day that would forever change their lives. The survivor’s stories are the most powerful aspect of any project, article, or book on the events of the UT tower shooting. Yet still many people have not heard these stories and many know very little about the shooting itself.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;What would have happened if the strong media presence that exists today had existed on August 1 1966? Would it have helped uncover the silenced memories of the murders? Or would they have been over-told? Few people had a platform to speak until years later, carrying around their stories without a voice. In 1999 Karan Elliot reflected on the shooting and wrote, “This tragedy has had a profound effect on my life and the memories will never fade.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Suzanne Rhoads wrote that “for years after that, when there was a loud noise, I would cringe.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These women never forgot how the shooting impacted their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In 1983 Sarah Rider interviewed Morris Hohmann who is a survivor of the shootings. He risked his life to retrieve the wounded and ended up getting shot in the process. He resents that he is remembered for being shot by the “notorious” Charles Whitman. His life after the shooting would be known for only one thing: that he was shot. On that August day, Morris picked up the first victim, Robert Boyer, and took him to Brackenridge Hospital. Robert Boyer was shot in the south mall and dragged into a building by onlookers, where police were able to get to him faster. After another rescue attempt, Morris got shot in his leg. The bullet didn’t exit or break a bone, but he nearly died from loss of blood and remained in the hospital for 21 days. Hohmann says that he has formed a bond with the people he knows who also experienced that day with him.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;There are people who chose to remember every day, and there are people who wish to forget it every day. In 1989, a UT student named Kevin Reed spoke about his memory of the event, saying that “It happened so long ago that it’s more of a curiosity than anything else, I think most students know about… what happened at the tower, but nobody likes to dwell on it.” Reed acknowledges that he is in a group of people who don’t know how to respond, even after so much time has passed. On the 25th anniversary, a UT spokesman said that there was nothing planned in terms of having a ceremony or service as the University of Texas sat in silence again.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/hurley/photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of memorial&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Alwyn Barr is a survivor who is now a 77-year-old retired college professor. He was at UT working on his Ph.D. that summer of 1966. That morning his wife was off campus and eight months pregnant, Barr remembers thinking that his child would grow up without a father. Now looking back, Barr reflects, “It would have been better if the campus police at The University of Texas in 1966 could have responded more quickly.” Barr remembers the event with a critical lens in light of the university’s current gun debates. “The general idea, of course, is that a university ought to be a place where you carry on debates and discussion about a variety of topics in the process of learning. But this is such a tricky thing, in the sense that there’s overtones of violence, and the fact that it’s there, at the University of Texas, where violence has taken place,” he stated. Although the university has been silent in the past about the tower shooting, more than enough time has passed, and people are speaking out. This year, finally, there are plans to have a larger memorial for the people who lost their lives on August 1, instead of the tiny plaque that exists now. Also, like Barr, many people fear the danger in having concealed carry because of shootings at UT and at other schools. Others justify concealed carry in the belief that they can protect themselves if such a shooting occurs again.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It is now time for The University of Texas to take stock of all of these stories and to find a way to break the silence behind the shootings.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Karan Russ Elliott. “Tower Garden Reflections.” (1999): n. pag. 8:39am. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Suzanne Kain Rhoades. “Tower Garden Reflections.” (1999): n. pag. 3:33pm. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Morris Hohmann. Interview by Sara Rider. Austin History Center Oral History Transcript May 31, 1983: n. pag. Print. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“CAMPUS LIFE: University of Texas; Infamous Weapons Are Put Up for Sale.” &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;. n. pag., July 30, 1989. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dell Cameron. “How a Survivor of the 1966 UT Tower Massacre Sees Saturday’s ‘mock Shooting’” The Daily Dot. n. pag., December 11, 2015. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/aftermath</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/aftermath</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I Choose to Remember;&lt;br&gt; I Need to Forget</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Days after the 1966 UT tower shooting, the air on campus seemed stiff. Some survivors had been released from the hospital while the deceased had begun to be buried. The media buzzed and university officials scrambled to find ways to help the university community adjust to life after the tragedy. Years began to pass and slowly the moment began to fade. For some, the tower tragedy paved the way to an endless struggle to find peace with their experience. For others who had been on or near campus and who had shots fired at them or at their friends and loved ones, the day would remain a dark moment in their life.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;comments&quot; data-title=&quot;Suzanne Kain Rhoads’s reflections&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/reflections-comment-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/reflections-comment-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;comments&quot; data-title=&quot;Karan Russ Elliott’s reflections&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/reflections-comment-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/reflections-comment-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Stories submitted by survivors to the University’s ‘Tower Reflections’ program.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;For a university community, losing a student or professor in a mass killing can produce a whirlwind of emotions. Add to this the fact that this act of violence was perpetrated by a member of that same community. Charles Whitman, a university student, shot and wounded over 45 people. The victim and wounded list would include mothers, daughters, sons, husbands, wives, grandchildren, and fathers leaving deep wounds in the lives of their beloved and the communities they belonged to. To this day, the community of Austin continues to struggle with the effects of the tragedy of August 1, despite attempts to heal by university officials, leaders of the community, law enforcement, public agencies, and student groups.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Moments of violence in a community’s history can take on different forms. For some communities, these moments are embodied in acts of war, violations of rights, or other direct acts of aggression towards people by the state or some other large, powerful group, as in Rwanda, Nazi Germany, and Guatemala. Healing from these instances requires challenging and often painful recollections of the moment either through storytelling, reflection, or erecting and interacting with memorial structures. Physical memorials can be constructed as testimonies to the past to acknowledge an event, provide an avenue of healing, and as an effort to remind future generations of the community’s history. For some people, these memorials can be distressing, but for others, memorials offer an opportunity to reflect and reconcile.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Let us consider that as victims, we require or perhaps expect some sort of reparation for the pain or loss we experience. Reparations work to re-establish trust and provide compensation for past wrongs. Memorials can offer experiences of reparation and healing. Survivors can visit and reflect on the past through a visual or by receiving a public acknowledgment that gives the survivor a space to affirm their experiences. The significance of affirming a person’s experience can greatly reduce the toll of negative emotions often experienced after incidents of violence as described in “&lt;a href=&quot;/aftermath&quot;&gt;Aftermath: Remembering and Forgetting the UT Tower Shooting&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The right to reparation comes from a conceptual framework for dealing with the past constructed by Swiss Peace, an independent peace research foundation in Switzerland. It focuses on four pillars of reconciliation mostly geared towards recovery from government sponsored acts of violence. The four pillars include 1) the right to know 2) the right to justice 3) the right to reparations and 4) the guarantee of non-reoccurrence.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Today if you walk around the University of Texas at Austin, especially around the UT tower, you would never guess that one of the most gruesome campus murders of the 20th century occurred here. When people visit the re-opened observation deck of the tower they might hear some whispers about the shooting. Some may even quietly mention Charles Whitman’s name. For many of those with memories of the shooting, the lack of remembrance and commemoration is striking. But how can or how should a community remember the incident of August 1? Who should be in charge of such a task? Many would argue that the university holds the principal responsibility for spearheading efforts to heal from this tragedy, but perhaps that only scratches the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In the minds of some, universities are responsible for nurturing the next generation of society’s members. Pastor Larry Bethune called this the sacred trust of families during his initial conversations with UT officials about establishing a memorial around the 33rd anniversary. In the case of the UT tower shooting, the university did not contribute directly to the violence nor did it ignore its responsibilities in the immediate aftermath. In fact, as noted in the article “&lt;a href=&quot;/the-university-response&quot;&gt;The University Response: A Product of the Times&lt;/a&gt;,” the university discreetly set up initiatives to aid the direct survivors and victims either through special academic considerations for returning students or fundraising efforts for the wounded and deceased. Resentment and anger from the survivors, as well as other Austinites, grew when the university failed to erect any sort of public apology or remembrance structure until decades later.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As the university and Austin community approach the 50th anniversary of the shooting, readers can most clearly see this frustration at the lack of a satisfactory remembrance effort by reading news articles or comments posted on blogs and social networking sites. In 2016, an independent group consisting of some survivors of the UT tower shooting have initiated an effort to erect a memorial, but this memorial is not the first. Several efforts at memorialization have been attempted by both the university as well as the Austin police department, the faith based community, and more recent university students. These memorials include gardens, plaques, a walking tour, and archival collections.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The first memorial initiative occurred in 1996 when a group of faith based groups apart from the university held a prayer vigil in an attempt to heal and reclaim the violent space for the community.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As Pastor Larry Bethune recalls, this prayer vigil grew out of discussions with UT professor Rosa Eberly, who in the 1990s had begun to teach “The UT Tower and Public Memory,” a course aimed at teaching students about civic engagement and rhetoric. Eberly belonged to the same faith community as Pastor Bethune, senior pastor of the Baptist University Church, and helped to organize the prayer vigil. Archival records seem to indicate that the university finally reacted to the frustrations shortly after the prayer vigil. In 1999, one year after Larry R. Faulkner became President of UT Austin, the Board of Regents approved Faulkner’s request to initiate a planning group to investigate the best way to commemorate the incident. Typed notes from a meeting between Faulkner and one of his assistants point to the fact that despite the years, community members continued to pressure the university for some memorial action. In the notes, Faulkner references a letter from a 1982 UT graduate commenting on the “overdue” need for a memorial to provide “closure” and “a permanent recognition of the victims of the tower shootings of 1966.”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/tower-garden.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tower Garden&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Because of his involvement with the 30th anniversary, the university sought the help of Pastor Bethune in planning for the university’s first attempt at memorializing the tragic event. Bethune joined the core group as they met throughout the summer of 1999, before the planned August 1 dedication of the memorial garden that would then be followed by the reopening of the tower on September 15, 1999, discussed in more detail in “&lt;a href=&quot;/the-specter-of-the-tower&quot;&gt;The Specter of the Tower&lt;/a&gt;”. On August 1, 1999 at the Turtle Pond now called the Reflection Garden, the university held a memorial service where it lowered the flags to half-staff, President Faulkner gave remarks, and the tower was darkened as is customary during moments of grief for the university.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/tower-garden-reflection.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Reflection in Pond&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;During this time the university also passed out forms similar to the UT Remembers forms for members of the community to write reflections on paper or via email of their lost one. These reflections are then placed inside the University permanent archives.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/reflections-form.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Form for UT Remembers&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Individuals could also &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.utexas.edu/events/tower&quot;&gt;submit their reflections via email&lt;/a&gt;,  a page currently unavailable, but accessible through the Internet Archive’s Wayback Machine with the last capture date of April 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/online-form.png&quot; alt=&quot;Online Form for Tower Reflections&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In January of 2007, shortly after the 40th anniversary, University of Texas officials put a bronze plaque in the garden near the tower as a memorial “to those who died, to those who were wounded, and to the countless other victims who were immeasurably affected by the tragedy,”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/tower-garden-plaque.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tower Garden Plaque&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Action taken by the University always seemed to coincide with other mass shootings on high school and university campuses such as the Columbine and Virginia Tech shootings, April 20th, 1999 and April 16, 2007 respectively. Other somewhat documented memorialization efforts came from non-university groups: the Austin Police Department Tower Heroes plaque inscription in 2008 located in the far southwest side of Austin and a student led walking memorial tour of campus in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/plaque-fullsize.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;plaque&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/carbajal/plaque.jpg&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    “Tower Heroes.” Plaque located at the Travis County Precinct 3 building at 8656B W Texas 71, Austin, TX 78735.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Despite all these attempts, the general public continues to decry an absence of remembrance. Do we attribute this frustration to a lack of awareness of the efforts by the university or do we recognize the depth of the pain experienced by this community? As Pastor Bethune mentions during his oral history, everyone deals with loss in a different way and for different lengths of time. As seen through other memorializations such as the 9/11 Ground Zero Site, the Columbine Memorial, and the Ntarama Church in Rwanda, directly impacted communities and those who felt the after effects approached healing in diverse ways.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As observers, we should acknowledge that while the effort to pay respect to the deceased and wounded did not come to fruition until 30 years after the tragedy, the university did eventually act. The discussions held behind closed doors among the dedication planning group members according to Pastor Bethune included thoughtful and purposeful actions, but due to funding constraints and resistance from unnamed individuals, the envisioned dedication fell short. Even the archive collecting attempt fizzled due to little publicity and awareness of its existence. For many new Austinites as well as those who experienced the UT tower shooting firsthand, the attempts at memorialization have yet to be enough. Perhaps they will never be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gray bar references&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Charles Bowden. “The Tower Tragedy.” &lt;em&gt;Esquire&lt;/em&gt;, January 29, 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esquire.com/features/ESQ0299-FEB_AMERICA_rev_&quot;&gt;http://www.esquire.com/features/ESQ0299-FEB_AMERICA_rev_&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Framing Public Memory&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Kendall R. Philipps. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“A Conceptual Framework for Dealing with the Past: Holism in Principle and Practice.” Dealing with the Past Background Paper. Swiss Peace, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Rosa Eberly. “Consider an Educational Memorial for UT Tower Shootings.” &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 28, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mystatesman.com/news/news/opinion/eberly-consider-an-educational-memorial-for-ut-tow/nqrkL/&quot;&gt;http://www.mystatesman.com/news/news/opinion/eberly-consider-an-educational-memorial-for-ut-tow/nqrkL/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Finding Healing.” &lt;em&gt;Lampasas Dispatch Record&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lampasasdispatchrecord.com/news/2011-11-11/Front_Page/Finding_healing.html&quot;&gt;http://www.lampasasdispatchrecord.com/news/2011-11-11/Front_Page/Finding_healing.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Kenneth E. Foote. &lt;em&gt;Shadowed Ground : America’s Landscapes of Violence and Tragedy&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. Rev. and updated, rev. ed. Austin: University of Texas Press, 2003. &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=nlebk&amp;amp;AN=130398&amp;amp;site=ehost-live&quot;&gt;http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;amp;db=nlebk&amp;amp;AN=130398&amp;amp;site=ehost-live&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Kirsten Foot, Barbara Warnick, and Steven M. Schneider. “Web-Based Memorializing After September 11: Toward a Conceptual Framework.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication&lt;/em&gt; 11, no. 1 (November 1, 2005): 72-96. doi:10.1111/j.1083-6101.2006.tb00304.x.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Craig Hlavaty. “47 Years Later, Whitman’s Tower Shooting Still a Haunting Memory for Texans.” &lt;em&gt;The Texican&lt;/em&gt;, August 1, 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.chron.com/thetexican/2013/08/47-years-later-whitmans-tower-shooting-still-a-haunting-memory-for-texans/&quot;&gt;http://blog.chron.com/thetexican/2013/08/47-years-later-whitmans-tower-shooting-still-a-haunting-memory-for-texans/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Landscape Architect and Visual Artist Chosen to Redesign Tower Garden at.” &lt;em&gt;UT News | The University of Texas at Austin&lt;/em&gt;, February 8, 2002. &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.utexas.edu/2002/02/08/nr_garden&quot;&gt;http://news.utexas.edu/2002/02/08/nr_garden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Marlen Luciano. “A Unique Memorial.” Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.jmu.edu/wrtcworkshop/a-unique-memorial/&quot;&gt;https://sites.jmu.edu/wrtcworkshop/a-unique-memorial/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Peter Jan Margry and Cristina Sanchez-Carretero. &lt;em&gt;Grassroots Memorials : The Politics of Memorializing Traumatic Death&lt;/em&gt;. 1st ed. New York, NY: Berghahn Books, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Memorial Plaque in Tower Garden Commemorates Victims of Aug. 1, 1966 Shooting Tragedy.” &lt;em&gt;UT News | The University of Texas at Austin&lt;/em&gt;, January 10, 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.utexas.edu/2007/01/10/tower_garden&quot;&gt;http://news.utexas.edu/2007/01/10/tower_garden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“A Moving Memorial for the Victims of the UT Tower Shootings | The Rag Blog.” Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theragblog.com/metro-alice-embree-a-moving-memorial-for-the-victims-of-the-ut-tower-shootings/&quot;&gt;http://www.theragblog.com/metro-alice-embree-a-moving-memorial-for-the-victims-of-the-ut-tower-shootings/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Justina Moloney. &lt;em&gt;Oral History with Larry Bethune&lt;/em&gt;. WAV file. Austin, TX, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Optimists Will Honor Heroes of Tower Day.” &lt;em&gt;The Austin American&lt;/em&gt; (1914-1973). August 21, 1966.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Valrie Plaza. &lt;em&gt;American Mass Murderers&lt;/em&gt;. Lulu.com, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Louise Purbick, Jim Auich, and Graham Dawson, eds. &lt;em&gt;Contested Spaces: Sites, Representations and Histories of Conflict&lt;/em&gt;. New York, NY: Palgrave MacMillan, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Mary Ann Roser. “New Memorial Planned to Mark 50th Anniversary of UT Tower…” &lt;em&gt;Austin American- Statesman&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mystatesman.com/news/news/local/new-memorial-planned-to-mark-50th-anniversary-of-u/nqnXC/&quot;&gt;http://www.mystatesman.com/news/news/local/new-memorial-planned-to-mark-50th-anniversary-of-u/nqnXC/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Jena R. Schwake. “Who Is Columbine? Forgetting the Public in Contemporary Memorial Sites.” M.A., Colorado State University, 2015. &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.proquest.com/docview/1717575798/abstract/C0BE94BD8B124A50PQ/1&quot;&gt;http://search.proquest.com/docview/1717575798/abstract/C0BE94BD8B124A50PQ/1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Susan A. Sci. “(Re)thinking the Memorial as a Place of Aesthetic Negotiation.” &lt;em&gt;Culture, Theory and Critique&lt;/em&gt; 50, no. 1 (April 1, 2009): 41-57. doi:10.1080/14735780802696351.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Harriet F. Senie. “How the Columbine Memorial Missed an Opportunity We Should Have Seized.” Accessed April 28, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://historynewsnetwork.org/article/162369&quot;&gt;http://historynewsnetwork.org/article/162369&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Kelsey Sheridan. “45th Anniversary of UT Shooting Marked With Dedication Ceremony.” Accessed April 28, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://kut.org/post/45th-anniversary-ut-shooting-marked-dedication-ceremony&quot;&gt;http://kut.org/post/45th-anniversary-ut-shooting-marked-dedication-ceremony&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Deborah Tedford. “University of Texas Shooting Remembered.” &lt;em&gt;NPR.org&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=9619382&quot;&gt;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=9619382&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Telling the Stories of the Whitman Shooting [Podcast].” &lt;em&gt;The Alcalde&lt;/em&gt;, April 4, 2014. &lt;a href=&quot;http://alcalde.texasexes.org/2014/04/telling-the-stories-of-the-whitman-shooting-podcast/&quot;&gt;http://alcalde.texasexes.org/2014/04/telling-the-stories-of-the-whitman-shooting-podcast/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Tower Garden’ Ceremony Scheduled for Aug. 1.” &lt;em&gt;UT News | The University of Texas at Austin&lt;/em&gt;, July 19, 1999. &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.utexas.edu/1999/07/19/tower-garden-ceremony-scheduled-for-aug-1&quot;&gt;http://news.utexas.edu/1999/07/19/tower-garden-ceremony-scheduled-for-aug-1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Tower Reflection Submission,” n.d. UT Remembers Records Box 2F472 1998-2002.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;James Tyner, Savina Sirik, and Samuel Henkin. “Violence and the Dialectics of Landscape: Memorialization in Cambodia.” &lt;em&gt;Geographical Review&lt;/em&gt; 104, no. 3 (July 1, 2014): 277-93. doi:10.1111/j.1931-0846.2014.12026.x.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“U. Texas’s Tower Garden Memorial For 1966 Shooting Victims.” &lt;em&gt;Austinist&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://austinist.com/2012/04/16/u_texass_tower_garden_memorial_for.php&quot;&gt;http://austinist.com/2012/04/16/u_texass_tower_garden_memorial_for.php&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Didn’t Shut down after 1966 Tower Shooting, but the Violence Left Its Mark.” &lt;em&gt;Valley Morning Star&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 21, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.valleymorningstar.com/news/article_73692574-d29e-5cd4-8d97-3c3fbf6c75ff.html&quot;&gt;http://www.valleymorningstar.com/news/article_73692574-d29e-5cd4-8d97-3c3fbf6c75ff.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Remembers 1966 Tower Shooting Victims.” Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.statesman.com/news/news/local/ut-remembers-1966-tower-shooting-victims/ngsgk/&quot;&gt;http://www.statesman.com/news/news/local/ut-remembers-1966-tower-shooting-victims/ngsgk/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Remembers Submission Form.” University of Texas, n.d. UT Remembers Records Box 2F472 1998-2002.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Remembers Submission Online Form,” n.d. &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20150430214855/http://www.utexas.edu/events/tower.thoughts.html&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20150430214855/http://www.utexas.edu/events/tower.thoughts.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Tower Shooting Survivors Creating Long-Overdue Memorial.” &lt;em&gt;KTBC Fox&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fox7austin.com/news/local-news/109775042-story&quot;&gt;http://www.fox7austin.com/news/local-news/109775042-story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Students Remember Tower Shooting Victims – The Daily Texan.” Accessed April 28, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailytexanonline.com/2014/08/02/ut-students-remember-tower-shooting-victims-0&quot;&gt;http://www.dailytexanonline.com/2014/08/02/ut-students-remember-tower-shooting-victims-0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“UT Tower Shooting.” &lt;em&gt;The Alcalde&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed April 28, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://alcalde.texasexes.org/tag/uttower-shooting/&quot;&gt;http://alcalde.texasexes.org/tag/uttower-shooting/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/i-choose-to-remember</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/i-choose-to-remember</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Fitting Memorial</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To burden others with your problems – are they problems? – is not right – however&lt;br /&gt;
  To carry them is akin to carrying a fused bomb – &lt;br /&gt;
  I wonder if the fuse can be doused – &lt;br /&gt;
  If it is doused what will be gained&lt;br /&gt;
  Will the gain be worth the effort put forth&lt;br /&gt;
  But&lt;br /&gt;
  Should one who considers himself strong, surrender to an enemy he considers so trivial and despicable&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;Charles Whitman, &lt;cite&gt;excerpted from his diary, Gary M. Lavergne Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Charles Whitman wrote these lines sometime in early 1964. We know this only because he tells us so: at the top of the page, Whitman made a notation in the midnight hours of August 1, 1966, explaining the year as a time “when I was in a similar feeling as I have been lately.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That “fused bomb” was detonating as he wrote. Earlier that evening, Whitman had begun to unburden his “problems” onto the two women he supposedly held most dear and would continue to do so later that day, onto dozens of other innocent victims and their families, communities, and friends. That explosion reverberated throughout the country, which found itself at a loss over how a “hitherto sane individual,” and an “all-American boy,” no less, could commit such senseless acts of violence.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/johnston/lightning-strike.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Whitman medical record&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Whitman had a variety of unusual medical issues – an “unusually thin” skull, a “pecan-sized” brain tumor, and, as shown here, he was struck by lightning while stationed at Guantanamo Bay.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The debate over what made Charles Whitman “snap,” as it’s often put, began the day of his killings and will likely never end. Physicians, investigators, and researchers have spent years documenting his troubled home life, drug abuse, the infamous “pecan-sized” tumor discovered in his brain, and the personal demons he described with disturbingly clinical self-reflection. Certain additional, relevant details of his life have received surprisingly little attention. Some are simply bizarre, like the fact that he was once caught in a phone booth struck by lightning.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Lightning strike survivors typically experience some level of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lightningsafety.noaa.gov/medical.shtml&quot;&gt;long-term cognitive disabilities&lt;/a&gt;. More surprisingly, nobody bothered to get the perspective of his wife Kathy or her family about Whitman until just a couple of years ago, despite his admission to beating her on more than one occasion. Those perspectives have turned out to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://catapult.co/stories/listening-to-kathy&quot;&gt;quite damning&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, speculation continues as to whether Whitman suffered from psychosis brought on by amphetamine-induced sleep deprivation and neuroscientists remain fascinated by the tumor and how much pressure it may or may not have exerted on his amygdala.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Despite advances in neuroscience and psychology, satisfying answers to these questions continue to intrigue – and elude – us.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Immediately after the shooting, Texas Governor John Connally convened a thirty-two person expert committee to answer these very questions. Contrary to statements by individual practitioners, the committee’s report was decidedly inconclusive.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Whitman’s body was embalmed before the autopsy, which made it impossible to conclusively check for drugs. His brain was damaged from the gunshot wounds that killed him. And the team lacked a recent psychiatric evaluation. The task force was forced to conclude that they found it “impossible to make a formal psychiatric diagnosis,” and “the application of existing knowledge of organic brain function does not enable us to explain the actions of Whitman on August first.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/johnston/brain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Dr. Chenar&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Archival wire print of Dr. Coleman de Chenar, who performed Whitman’s autopsy and concluded that the tumor pictured here was not the cause of the shootings.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The curiosity about Whitman and his motives has largely overshadowed an important part of the Governor’s Report. The committee’s recommendations on how to deal with the aftermath of the shootings, and try to prevent similar events in the future, went far beyond symbolic “thoughts and prayers.” The report helped to galvanize fundamental reform of mental health care practices at the University of Texas – a side of the tragedy’s legacy that has largely been forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Immediately after recommending the provision of aid to victims of the shooting, the committee’s next recommendation was “that The University of Texas have the best possible health program in the broadest meaning of the term for both students and faculty.” Mental health, in particular, was paramount. “For the university student, undergoing one of the most stressful periods of his development, a mental health program is considered vital – not only through implementation of known practices but also through ongoing research and application of new knowledge,” the report read. “No more fitting memorial to those who suffered from this tragic event, and no more worthwhile effort than to anticipate or prevent similar catastrophes, can be conceived.”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The scope and structure of UT student health services in 1966 was dramatically different than what it is today. Psychiatric and mental health services were provided by the “Mental Hygiene Clinic” of what was then called the Student Health Center. In addition, there was a Testing and Counseling Center that fell under the purview of the Dean of Students. While SHC’s mental health services were primarily clinical in nature, the mandate of the TCC in the mid-1960s was losing focus by the day. While originally intended to address academic issues, it had become increasingly clear that the stress and anxiety of university life – inside the classroom and out – called for a more holistic approach to student wellness.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Students at time were vocal about the quality and availability of counseling services on campus. Advice on both academic and personal issues, they said, was often cursory or unavailable. In March 1967, a committee of students from the university’s YMCA and YWCA called for reform due to a “student feeling that the University’s counseling system has been unable to respond adequately to some student needs and problems on this campus.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Since counseling was still regarded as a primarily academic issue, it was relegated in part to professors, who sometimes dismissed these duties as an undesired “extra job.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In a column for &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt; two months after the shooting, Student Government President Clif Drummond called for the university to “re-define counseling and put students’ needs into a more realistic perspective.”&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Now, I do not think it is the duty solely of the faculty to counsel. This aspect belongs also to professionals, student advisers, parents, and good friends. What is needed is simply to evaluate the roles and responsibilities of each of these counselors. Then their roles should be integrated into a broad program which has a coherent philosophical basis – not one which is fragmented.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Mental health professionals at the university were acutely aware that the school’s approach to mental health was fragmented. Dr. Ira Iscoe, a noted professor of psychology at UT, admitted that the TCC had developed in a “somewhat patchwork fashion.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This result was due to a combination of perpetually inadequate funding, a burgeoning student population, and changing attitudes towards the responsibilities of a university in the well being of its students. In fact, Iscoe and others had already begun a review of UT’s counseling policies several months before Whitman’s rampage. The UT Board of Regents had adopted a resolution in April 1966 to conduct the review, and Chancellor Harry Ransom convened the Ad-Hoc Committee on Student Counseling to carry out that task.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The committee was comprised largely of professionals from UT’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://hogg.utexas.edu/&quot;&gt;Hogg Foundation for Mental Health&lt;/a&gt;, which has been a pioneer in the field of mental health issues in Texas for the past 75 years. The Foundation played a key role in the restructuring and expansion of UT’s mental health services after the tower shooting. “Tragedy may serve as an immobilizer or a catalyst,” says its &lt;a href=&quot;https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/handle/2152/21002&quot;&gt;annual report&lt;/a&gt; for 1966. In this case, tragedy “accelerated programs already planned concerning campus mental health.” Indeed, the Foundation and its director, Robert Lee Sutherland, had been pushing for counseling reform on campus for years. In a letter to Ransom shortly after the shooting, Sutherland expressed frustration at past “research and pilot projects in counseling” that had been valuable but “fragmentary and inadequate,” and regret that a recent psychiatric consultation project was not continued past its trial year. “Its need,” Sutherland stressed, “is dramatically imperative in light of the Whitman case and other evidences of student problems.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We will never know whether the tower shooting could have been prevented by a reformed counseling system. What is certain, and what Sutherland was most concerned with, was that reform was needed to address “the educational progress and counseling needs of 28,600 students.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The Ad-Hoc Committee made its recommendations at the end of 1966. The TCC was split in two, and counseling services were expanded and re-defined. Additional annual budgetary funds were appropriated, approximately $250,000 for the SHC and its Mental Hygiene Clinic, and $103,000 for expanded student counseling services.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Counselors were appointed to dormitories and a 24-hour hotline was established in the Dean of Student’s office.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The hotline quickly demonstrated that the school had identified an unfulfilled need in the student community – students placed 1,088 calls to the hotline specifically requesting counseling during the 1967-68 academic year.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In addition, the Hogg Foundation &lt;a href=&quot;https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/handle/2152/21002&quot;&gt;cited&lt;/a&gt; grants for “150 projects supervised in the last 12 months […] for pilot projects in counseling and related approaches” in its 1966 annual report. In one key development, it noted that “increased support by the administration and faculty” had been helpful for expanding mental health services. Support for these projects continued past the typical trial year, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/handle/2152/21027&quot;&gt;later annual reports&lt;/a&gt;. There was also a gradual shift in counseling philosophy. In an October 1967 follow-up, Dr. Iscoe noted that “the question of positive mental health is assuming more importance than the question of dealing with severely emotionally disturbed students.” This approach held that counseling should be available to all students on UT’s campus – not just those in dire straits. He clarified that the Mental Hygiene Clinic would be in charge of cases with “a clear psychiatric component,” but that the new Counseling Center should cooperate with the Clinic in appropriate situations (immediate and longer term considerations).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Any discussion of the mental health consequences of the Whitman shootings must include the role of Dr. Maurice Dean Heatly. Perhaps the most scandalous revelation from the university in the days following the shootings was that Whitman had gone to the Student Health Center in March 1966 and told Dr. Heatly, a staff psychiatrist, that he was “thinking about going up on the tower with a deer rifle and start shooting people.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Heatly did graduate from medical school – he was in the class of 1939 at Baylor – but he was not board certified to practice psychiatry.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; At the time, no such certification was required to practice psychiatry in Texas. Any licensed physician was free to do so. Be that as it may, our knowledge of Heatly’s counseling style does not inspire confidence. Writing for &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt; on their twentieth anniversary of the shooting, former student William Helmer &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/the-madman-on-the-tower/&quot;&gt;recalled&lt;/a&gt; the sessions he and his wife had with Dr. Heatly:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;My visit consisted mainly of listening to him talk on the telephone with the driller who was putting in a water well on his ranch, after which he gave me a prescription for Librium. My wife came back from her visit crying and said that after pretty much baring her soul, his advice to her was “Grow up.”&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It is hard to say whether Helmer’s experience with Heatly was typical or not. What we do know is that the doctor was paid a total of $36,880 (about $265,000 by today’s standards) for his part-time work at the university between 1963 and 1967.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:18&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:18&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We also know that Heatly’s career was marred by allegations of cronyism. His brother was the infamously iron-fisted State Senate Appropriations Committee Chairman William S. Heatly. In 1964, auditors found that Maurice Heatly had been paid $40 to $50 more per hour than other psychiatric consultants for his work for the Texas Department of Corrections and the Texas Youth Commission.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The doctor denied any impropriety, and the whole affair was brushed off as an example of the TDC’s “woefully poor management techniques.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Allegations of misconduct in the Whitman case were similarly dismissed. Mental health practitioners at the time generally agreed that there was nothing he could have done to prevent the shootings later that year. “Thousands of people – and I mean literally thousands talk to doctors about having such feelings,” University of Chicago Psychiatrist Robert S. Daniels told &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; – “Nearly all of them are just talking.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In a statement that reminds us of the political climate in 1966, New Jersey Psychiatrist Henry A. Davidson put a finer point on it: “We are in a situation now where there is enormous pressure for civil rights. The idea of locking someone up on the basis of a psychiatrist’s opinion that he might in the future be violent could be repugnant.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Governor Connally was even more forgiving, saying “I think Dr. Heatly was absolutely correct in the actions he took.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:23&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:23&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Mental health professionals at UT noted that there was no psychological test to identify potential killers and Dr. Iscoe characterized Whitman’s actions as an “enigma.” “It would be easier to understand,” said Iscoe, “if he had been one of the campus Beatniks, bearded, unkempt and on scholastic probation, aimlessly protesting a variety of things and meandering along with no purpose in life. Which would you keep your eye on as a potential trouble maker?”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:24&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:24&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; While it is difficult to judge Heatly’s responsibility in the Whitman case, suffice to say that he would probably not be hired by today’s Counseling and Mental Health Center – each of the center’s current M.D.s holds a board certification in psychiatry.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In heeding the call of the Governor’s Report, the University of Texas refused to be defined by tragedy. The shootings were a wake-up call to the school’s administration, which stepped up to support the Hogg Foundation in reforming and expanding access to mental health and counseling services on campus. General health services improved as well. By 1969, the alumni magazine, the Alcalde, was singing the praises of the newly augmented Student Health Center.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:25&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Today, UT Austin is &lt;a href=&quot;http://activemindsblog.org/meet-the-university-of-texas-at-austin-a-2015-healthy-campus-award-winner/&quot;&gt;recognized as a leader&lt;/a&gt; among American universities for its approach to physical and mental wellness. The quality and scope of these programs continues to improve, as do efforts to expand access. That expanded access, however, has been met – and exceeded. Demand for mental health services on campus is currently well beyond capacity. In some cases, waiting periods for a counseling appointment in 2015 stretched to over a month. Other barriers to access have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailytexanonline.com/2015/09/24/cmhc-price-hike-burdens-at-risk-students&quot;&gt;caused concern&lt;/a&gt; among the student community, in particular, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailytexanonline.com/2015/09/18/cmhc-raises-prices-for-individual-counseling-psychiatric-sessions&quot;&gt;fee hike&lt;/a&gt; implemented this year for individual counseling and psychiatric sessions. With the implementation of “campus carry” beginning on August 1, 2016 – fifty years to the day since the shootings – this demand is likely to increase. Some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailytexanonline.com/2015/11/02/campus-carry-remains-contentious-issue&quot;&gt;faculty are concerned&lt;/a&gt; that the combination of mental stress and access to guns will put students at increased risk for suicide. While the university’s Working Group for Campus Carry policy &lt;a href=&quot;https://utexas.app.box.com/v/ccworkinggroup-finalreport&quot;&gt;called&lt;/a&gt; for the administration to “examine the level of resources devoted to mental health services and better publicize the existence of mental health services already available to the UT community,” the president’s policy recommendations &lt;a href=&quot;https://utexas.app.box.com/v/campus-carry-report&quot;&gt;did not mention plans&lt;/a&gt; to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As we approach this fateful anniversary, it is worth pausing to reflect on how dramatically the mental health environment on campus has changed. And why it has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Charles Whitman’s diary, Gary M. Lavergne Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These quotations are from J.W. Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration, Bureau of Drug Abuse Control, from the files of the Texas Department of Public Safety at the Texas State Library and Archives Commission, and Dr. Maurice D. Heatly as quoted in Gary Lavergne’s &lt;em&gt;A Sniper in the Tower&lt;/em&gt;. University of North Texas Press, 1997, pg. 234 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;From “General and Medical Background Information for the Whitman Case Requested by Governor John B. Connally,” Ira Iscoe Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a selection of the scientific debate on this topic, see: Shelley Batts, “Brain lesions and their implications in criminal responsibility.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral sciences &amp;amp; the law&lt;/em&gt; 27.2 (2009): 261-272; Kristina E. Donahue, “Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging and the Law Today: The Brain Is Reliable as a Mitigating Factor, but Unreliable as an Aggravating Factor or as a Method of Lie Detection.” &lt;em&gt;U. Balt. L. Rev.&lt;/em&gt; 42 (2012): 857; and David Eagleman, “The brain on trial.” &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; 7 (2011). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dr. Coleman de Chenar, who conducted Whitman’s autopsy, said publicly that the tumor “could not have had any influence on the psychic behavior” of the shooter. As quoted by the AP in “Grand Jury Rules Killer Was ‘Crazy, Deranged’ Man.” &lt;em&gt;Waukesha Daily Freeman&lt;/em&gt;, August 5, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Report to the Governor, Medical Aspects, Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe,” Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Interim Report of Counseling Committee, University of Texas YMCA and YWCA, March 1967,” from the Robert L. Sutherland Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cliff Drummond, “University Asked to Re-evaluate Counselor System.” &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt;, September 29, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ira Iscoe, “Counseling Center, University of Texas, Austin, Texas, Immediate and Longer Term Considerations,” October 27, 1967, in the Robert L. Sutherland Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Letter from Ronald Sutherland to Harry Ransom, August 25, 1966, in the Ronald L. Sutherland Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Letter from Ronald Sutherland to Harry Ransom, August 25, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe Follow-up Study” September 8, 1967, in the Gary L. Lavergne Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe Follow-up Staudy” September 8, 1967. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Report on the “Twenty-Four Hour Telephone and Counseling and Referral Service, The University of Texas at Austin,” April 1968, in the Robert L. Sutherland Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ira Iscoe, “Counseling Center, University of Texas, Austin, Texas, Immediate and Longer Term Considerations,” October 27, 1967, in the Robert L. Sutherland Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dr. Maurice Dean Heatly report on Charles Whitman, March 29, 1966, in the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;UPI, “Chairman’s Brother is Well Paid.” &lt;em&gt;Bonham Daily Favorite&lt;/em&gt;, April 20, 1969. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:18&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;UPI, “Heatly’s Relatives Get $142,025 in Pay.” &lt;em&gt;Dallas Morning News&lt;/em&gt;, April 25, 1969. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:18&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Patti Kilday, “TDC reviewing fees paid to brother of former legislator.” &lt;em&gt;Dallas Time Herald&lt;/em&gt;, January 21, 1964. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Prison system wasteful.” &lt;em&gt;Amarillo Daily News&lt;/em&gt;, January 30, 1964. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Madman in the Tower.” &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; August 12, 1966, p. 19. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Madman in the Tower.” &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; August 12, 1966, p. 19. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:23&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Psychiatrist to Blame, Sniper’s Father Says.” &lt;em&gt;Houston Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, August 4, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:23&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:24&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mary Rice Brogan, “Whitman Drawn to Famed Tower.” &lt;em&gt;Houston Chronicle&lt;/em&gt;, August 2, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:24&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:25&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anne D. Robinson, “Here’s to your health.” &lt;em&gt;The Alcalde&lt;/em&gt;, April 1969. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:25&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/a-fitting-memorial</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/a-fitting-memorial</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>“The Eyes of the World Are Upon You, Texas”</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;When Charles Whitman shot at innocent passersby from atop the University of Texas tower on August 1, 1966, he shocked the country and, according to the local newspapers, became the “Greatest Mass Slayer in History.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Media across the country tried to explain what occurred to their stunned readers, and in Austin, three newspapers, &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt;, UT Austin’s student newspaper, and the &lt;em&gt;Austin American&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, the citywide newspapers, shaped the public understanding of the events for shocked Austinites and UT students.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nationwide, newspapers reported extensively on the “sniper in Texas” and closely scrutinized the events of that day.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; All these articles attempted to answer the same question: “Why?” &lt;em&gt;The Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, published jointly on Sundays through 1973, chose to focus on Whitman’s mental and medical state, while &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt; highlighted student voices and their efforts to assist those affected.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;newspaper-front-pages&quot; data-title=&quot;Front page of The Austin American&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/garza/american.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/garza/american-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;newspaper-front-pages&quot; data-title=&quot;Front page of The Austin Statesman&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/garza/statesman.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/garza/statesman-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Front pages of &lt;i&gt;The Austin American&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/i&gt;.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;h2 id=&quot;student-voices-heard&quot;&gt;Student Voices Heard&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt;, printed as &lt;em&gt;The Summer Texan&lt;/em&gt; during UT’s summer session that year, acted as a voice of the student body. The student newspaper had a regular column, “The Firing Line,” for students to submit short comments to the paper reacting to current news. On August 9, 1966, “The Firing Line” was awash with opinions about the past week’s tragedy.  Like the city newspapers, students’ commentary on “The Firing Line” raised many questions about the reasons Whitman chose to fire at innocent people from atop the tower.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The students made various suggestions to improve safety, called for permanently or temporarily closing the tower, and recommended ways to commemorate those wounded and killed.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/garza/firing-line-fullsize.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;firingline&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/garza/firing-line.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scan of Firing Line page from The Summer Texan&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;The Summer Texan&lt;/i&gt; August 9, 1966, “The Firing Line”
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The tragic event affected people with ties to UT around the world. Pete Coneway expressed his condolences and said “that the world understands this terrible crime as the act of an insane person.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Nancy Kowert, John De La Garza, Jr., and David Gray each said the tower should remain open despite its tarnished image. Gray wrote “the Observation Deck of the tower should remain open – not for the curious nor the morbid, but so that people might see the bullet scars and blood stains and not forget that Whitman was indicative of something wrong in our society.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; H. Gray Merriam’s submission, “Who’s Fault?,” [sic] echoed the same sentiments. Merriam did not view the “terror from the tower” as the act of one individual, and listed questions, wondering who to blame. The students generally did not feel the need to blame, but chose to move on, look to the future, and learn from a horrible event.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-theory-of-disaster-and-the-psychiatrists&quot;&gt;The “Theory of Disaster” and the Psychiatrists&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The joint &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt; released a special staff report on Sunday August 7, 1966 to try to explain Charles Whitman’s actions.  The first page outlined community repercussions of the tragic event and several psychiatrists’ thoughts on Whitman.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Derro Evans and Sara Speights, staff writers at the &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, viewed the shooting through a psychological and sociological lens, using Dr. Harry E. Moore’s “Theory of Disaster” to explain the responses of the UT community.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Dr. Moore was a sociologist at UT who passed away a month before the shooting. His theory consisted of four stages: disbelief, aid, survivor’s feelings, and scapegoating. They saw “disbelief” in students’ initial reactions, who thought the gunshots were construction noises.  Evans and Speights reported, as examples of “aid,” that many students ran out in the line of fire to help their fellow students. “Survivors’ feelings” were overwhelmingly uncertain: they did not know how to react. Many returned to campus the next day unsure of the next steps to take. As examples of scapegoating, they identified several targets of popular blaming: the psychiatrist who treated Whitman months before, police protocol, and the gun laws.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Underneath this article was “The Psychiatrists: Right Before and After the Tragedy” by Chris Whitcraft, another staff writer.  It detailed two different psychiatrist’s views of Whitman.  Dr. Maurice Dean Heatly, the psychiatrist at UT’s Student Health Center, met with Whitman on March 29, 1966.  Even though Whitman expressed his thoughts of “going up on the tower with a deer rifle and … shooting people,” Heatly determined Whitman had “no psychosis at all.”  Dr. John A. Boston, a private practitioner and part-time assistant professor of Special Education at UT, labeled Whitman as a paranoid schizophrenic.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Whitcraft interviewed Dr. Clarence R. Miller, superintendent of the Austin State Hospital, to offer a third opinion.  Miller said both men were right on the days they gave their diagnoses.   Whitman was the “golden boy,” and would not have been committed on the day he gave Dr. Heatly the now, rattling statement, Dr. Miller said.  He also added that Dr. Boston’s diagnosis is an easy one to make in hindsight.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sniper-had-a-tumor&quot;&gt;The Sniper had a Tumor&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;On the day after the shooting, &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt; presented another actor in the horrific incident. Plastered across the August 2, 1966 edition, the biggest headline on the page read: “Sniper Had a Tumor.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But, even though the headline suggested the tumor had an inherent effect on Whitman’s acts, the first sentence of the article states the opposite: “… an Austin pathologist conducting the post-mortem said he did not think it had a direct effect in sparking the massacre Monday.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Through the years since, the tumor has been the subject of controversy, with some articles claiming it did play a factor and others saying the tumor had no effect at all.  Perhaps journalists thought that citing the tumor created a sort of justification for such a senseless murder.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Another word stands out amongst the countless headlines printed in the days after Whitman’s act: “Sniper.” As the media tried to figure out who could commit such a terrible act, writers began piecing together a portrait of the man on the tower. “Sniper” jumped out as the most commonly used word to describe Whitman and it dominated the headlines, both local and nationwide. &lt;em&gt;LIFE&lt;/em&gt; magazine’s cover on August 12, 1966 stated “The Texas Sniper.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Was this term used to convey the accuracy with which Whitman shot that day? With the United States in the midst of the Vietnam War, was “sniper” a more recognizable term than “murderer,” a term that does not appear in any headlines?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Whitman’s portrayal in the media does not seem to shift over time. He is simultaneously called a “Good Man, Good Husband, Good Citizen” and “an Insane Killer.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-the-victims&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What about the victims?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Those affected by the tragedy, the dead and wounded, are written about in simple terms and often placed in small spaces among the columns dedicated to Whitman. Maybe because this was deemed the first mass murder, perhaps the media was not sure how to write about the victims aside from issuing obituary-like articles. However, &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt; continuously reported the collection of funds for victims and their families. On August 9, 1966, &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt; reported that the Ex-Students Association was setting up a special committee to look into ways to help the families of the victims. Their next issue had an article about the fund and how to contribute. A year later, &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt; reported that surviving victims received almost $2,000 in aid grants from the Association.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Unlike the city newspapers, which were more interested in explaining Whitman and his actions, the student journalists at UT wrote about the efforts made to help those within their community.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Over the years, the media has retraced the events of August 1, 1966 and continues to struggle with the same question: “Why?” The simplest question seems to be the hardest one to answer and the student and city newspapers have grasped at multiple solutions over the last fifty years. Newspapers served as the first line of information that shaped public opinion in 1966. Through their coverage of the events of August 1, 1966, &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Austin American&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;The Daily Texan&lt;/em&gt; tried to define Whitman, his actions, and the events that unfolded the days after. The various questions that journalists raised, days and even years after the event, seem to have no concrete answer. However, it shows our inherent need to know the simplest, yet hardest, question: Why?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Greatest Mass Slayer in History?,” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 2, 1966, Vol. 96, No. 6 edition, sec. Front Page, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In 1966, &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Austin American&lt;/em&gt; published separate editions despite being jointly owned by Charles E. Marsh and E. S. Fentress.  The Sunday Edition was printed as &lt;em&gt;The Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;United Press International, “Sniper in Texas U.Tower Kills 12, Hits 33; Wife, Mother Also Slain; Police Kill Him,” &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, August 2, 1966, 115 edition, sec. Front Page, ProQuest. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Firing Line,” &lt;em&gt;The Summer Texan&lt;/em&gt;, August 9, 1966, Vol. 66, No. 17 edition, The Daily Texan Microfilm, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Firing Line,” &lt;em&gt;The Summer Texan&lt;/em&gt;, August 9, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Firing Line,” &lt;em&gt;The Summer Texan&lt;/em&gt;, August 9, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Derro Evans and Sara Speights, “Sniper on the Tower,” &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 7, 1966, Vol. 42, No. 68 edition, sec. A, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Derro Evans and Sara Speights, “Reaction Under Stress,” &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 7, 1966, Vol. 42, No. 68 edition, sec. A, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chris Whitcraft, “The Psychiatrists: Right Before and After the Tragedy,” &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 7, 1966, Vol. 42, No. 68 edition, sec. A, microfilm, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Sniper Had a Tumor,” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 2, 1966, Vol. 96, No. 6 edition, sec. Front Page, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Sniper Had a Tumor,” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 2, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“The Texas Sniper,” &lt;em&gt;LIFE&lt;/em&gt;, August 12, 1966, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chris Whitcraft, “This Was Charles Whitman,” &lt;em&gt;Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 7, 1966, Vol. 42, No. 68 edition, sec. A, Richard T. Fleming University Writings Collection, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/how-austin-newspapers-covered-the-shooting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/how-austin-newspapers-covered-the-shooting</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The University Response</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In a press conference on the day after the tragedy, Chancellor Harry Ransom expressed his gratitude for those who displayed heroism saving victims while he powerlessly watched from his office in the tower. Would being an eyewitness of the shooting affect the decisions he made on behalf of the university? This question is hard to answer.  Much of the administrative response concerning the shooting was handled by Vice Chancellor Norman Hackerman of the Division of Academic Affairs. Hackerman notified professors of injured students asking them to provide special consideration due to the tragic circumstances. It is unclear what “special considerations” Hackerman meant, whether this related to classes missed due to time in the hospital or their emotional and mental well being.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;video-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1X5VEqJ&quot; id=&quot;first-video-link&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/moloney/first-video-poster.jpg&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;play-button&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;first-video-container&quot; style=&quot;display: none&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/interface/loader.svg&quot; class=&quot;loader&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
  $(&#39;#first-video-link&#39;).on(&#39;click&#39;, function(e) {
    e.preventDefault();
    $(&#39;#first-video-link&#39;).hide();
    $(&#39;#first-video-container&#39;).show();
    $.get(&#39;/video/moloney-first-video.html&#39;, function(data) {
      $(&#39;#first-video-container&#39;).html(data);
      });
  });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Video clip courtesy of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1X5VEqJ&quot;&gt;Texas Archive of the Moving Image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Money was raised by the UT Alumni Association and the Student Association to aid in the recovery of injured students in response to a suggestion from Chancellor Ransom. The university sent telegrams to injured students as well, concerned about their well being, although no effort was made to send out additional telegrams or letters to these same students. An inquiry was sent to Hackerman after this first batch of telegrams was sent asking “if you think it would be a good idea to send a [follow-up letter],” but no record can be found if this was done.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Classes were canceled on August 2, allowing students, faculty, and staff to grapple with the shocking events of the previous day. Flags were flown at half-mast in remembrance of UT victims the week after the shooting. Additionally, a separate memorial fund was created for Edna E. Townsley, the receptionist at the tower observation deck killed by Whitman and leaving two children behind. The tower observation deck was not closed in response to the shooting, but instead closed by the Texas Board of Regents in 1974 after a number of suicides.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/moloney/hackerman.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dr. Hackerman’s memorandum&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Dr. Hackerman’s memorandum asking for faculty to provide “special consideration” towards student’s injured during the shooting.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;These actions must have appeared sufficient at the time, but today seem to lack concern for those not physically injured by the shooting. Where was the concern for how everyone else on the campus would grapple with this event? Was the eventual neglect of the shooting the university’s attempt to return campus activities to their normal routine?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;No official commemoration or acknowledgment of the deadly tragedy took place in the years that followed.  Only after decades of neglect, some members of the public began to take &lt;a href=&quot;/aftermath&quot;&gt;remembering the shooting&lt;/a&gt; into their own hands. In 1996, Dr. Rosa Eberly, a rhetoric professor at UT, held an undergraduate class titled “The UT Tower and Public Memory.” Her students interpreted this class as a call to action; to gain access to the tower’s observation deck. These students wrote a letter to then president Robert Berdahl protesting the need to reopen the tower’s observation. They received a letter in response denying access on the basis of the official policy of the Texas Regents to keep the observation deck permanently closed At the 30th anniversary, in 1996, the University Baptist Church, close neighbor to the campus at 21st St and Guadalupe St., organized a commemorative event with University officials in attendance. Perhaps this reignited interest in remembering the shooting within the UT community. In 1999, a committee was formed by the university to create a memorial in remembrance of the UT Tower shooting. Why did the university wait this long to &lt;a href=&quot;/i-choose-to-remember&quot;&gt;create a memorial&lt;/a&gt; for the shooting, 33 years after the events? At that time, it seemed to Larry Faulkner, the sitting president of the university, that “the university’s stance had always seemed to be to try to erase what had happened, but with absolutely no success. It was like an injury that would never heal.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; President Faulkner was a graduate student in chemistry at UT in 1966, walking off of campus soon after Whitman began shooting.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/moloney/telegram.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Memo to Hackerman inquiring as to send additional telegrams to injured students.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;University officials in 1966 felt their expression of sympathy was enough. Moving on and resuming everyday university life was more important to them at that time. In the 1960s many people believed that traumatic events were best left to be dealt with in the private sphere, not openly as a community. Those deciding how the university would respond were products of a generation that acknowledged tragedy but did not deem it appropriate to discuss openly. Had Chancellor Ransom or Vice-Chancellor Hackerman realized how traumatic this event was to the victims and the community, perhaps the university’s actions might have been different. By 1999 though, it was striking to President Faulkner and others that the university had not acknowledged the victims in a more visible way. Today, trauma is often dealt with much more immediate action and commemoration, compared to an age when time passed before trauma was dealt with appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/moloney/handbill.jpg&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    The handbill dispersed for the Tower Memorial Garden Dedication August 1,  1999.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The Tower Memorial Garden, the product of President Faulkner and the committee’s efforts to memorialize the event, is a garden located just north of the tower intended to allow visitors to remember, reflect, and process through their grief. Funding constraints prevented the memorial garden from fully illustrating the UT committee’s design as a space to not only remember the shooting, but process through one’s grief as a result of any situation. The garden was dedicated on August 1, 1999, 33 years after the shooting. The dedication was well attended, many expressing in comment cards written afterwards how thankful they were to have a designated spot on the UT campus to remember those whose lives were lost that hot August day. At the time, though, the garden did not include any kind of signage memorializing the victims of the shooting. In addition to the garden, the tower observation deck was reopened later that month as a way to &lt;a href=&quot;/the-specter-of-the-tower&quot;&gt;reclaim the tower&lt;/a&gt; as a “symbol of education” and gain control over the tragic events of the shooting that occurred there. A memorial plaque was added to the garden in 2007, but did not include names of victims. Presently, a group not connected to the university is attempting to create a new memorial to the shooting, fifty years after the tragedy. Clearly, many people still find this garden and anonymous plaque insufficient to deal with the trauma of August 1, 1966.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In 1966 the university exhibited concern for the well-being of students directly affected by the shooting, so when did the UT and Austin community begin feeling that the university had not done enough? What is the appropriate role for a university administration to play when a tragic event happens on campus? What role does the administration play in shaping the ways the university community will continue to remember a traumatic event? Now that we understand more about the process of grief, perhaps we can provide counseling and services that aid communities to better process a tragic event on “safe place” like a university campus? These are questions people will continue to ask ourselves each year as any kind of tragedy occurs on a college campus.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gray bar references&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Colloff. “96 Minutes.” &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt;. January 20, 2013. April 1, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“A memorial fund honoring Edna Townsley.” UT President’s Office Box 80-50/35. Whitman, Charles Joseph, 1970, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Darro Evans and Sara Speights. “Sniper on the Tower.” &lt;em&gt;The Austin American-Statesman&lt;/em&gt; August 7, 1966: A17.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Flags at half-mast,” UT President’s  Office Box 80-50/35 Whitman, Charles Joseph, 1970, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Justina Moloney. &lt;em&gt;Oral History with Larry Bethune&lt;/em&gt;. WAV file. Austin, TX, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Neal Spelce. “The Neal Spelce Collection, No. 1 – UT Tower Shooting.” &lt;em&gt;Texas Archive of the  Moving Image&lt;/em&gt;. Texas Archive of the Moving Image. Accessed April 1, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Students injured on August 1st 1966,” UT President’s Office Box 80-50/35 Whitman, Charles  Joseph, 1970, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Telegrams sent to injured students”, UT President’s Office Box 80-50/35 Whitman, Charles  Joseph, 1970, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“The Tower Garden: A Garden of Reflection,” UT Remembers Records Box 2F472 1998-2002, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Telegrams sent to injured students”, UT President’s Office Box 80-50/35 Whitman, Charles Joseph, 1970, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Colloff. “96 Minutes.” &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt;. January 20, 2013. Accessed April 1, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Colloff. “96 Minutes.” &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/the-university-response</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/the-university-response</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Little Metal Bottle</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;There is no evidence that Charles Whitman was under the influence of drugs when he climbed the UT tower on August 1, 1966. An analysis of tissue from Whitman’s liver, stomach, kidney, and brain conducted by the Armed Forces Institute of Pathology turned up negative.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; An expert committee commissioned by Texas Governor John Connally concluded that although Whitman was known to take stimulants as a study aid, “there was no evidence of acute or chronic drug toxicity” on the day of the shootings.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As &lt;em&gt;A Sniper in the Tower&lt;/em&gt; author Gary Lavergne &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.garylavergne.com/whitman-why.htm&quot;&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt;, Whitman spent two days planning and executing the murders of his wife and mother, and the mass shooting of dozens of people, with the precision and calculation uncharacteristic of someone affected by an illicit substance.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;All of these statements are true. So why even raise the issue of drugs?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;There is an enormous gap in the discussion of the UT tower shooting when it comes to Whitman’s substance abuse. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration, Texas Board of Pharmacy, and the Governor’s Commission all investigated whether allegations that he took amphetamines “like candy,” routinely induced insomnia for days on end, and at times exhibited severely compromised cognition and behavior could have had any connection to his actions that day.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Their findings, particularly of the FDA, are disturbing to say the least - although not why you might expect. Regardless, those inquiries were derailed upon the discovery of the tumor in Whitman’s brain.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For sure, if there was anything in his body that made him “snap,” it must have been that.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/johnston/dexedrine.jpg&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Advertisements for Dexedrine in the 1960s appealed to anyone who simply felt the need for a pick-me-up.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As it turned out, the role of the tumor was just as inconclusive as the role of anything else.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; What’s more, the aforementioned tissue analysis actually tells us very little. Whitman’s body was embalmed prior to his autopsy, severely limiting the findings of any chemical analysis. Dexedrine, his amphetamine of choice, can only be detected through a urine sample, which was wholly unavailable.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But the Governor’s Report boiled it down to this:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;He took stimulating drugs to assist him in keeping academic deadlines, the net effect of which was further loss of efficiency and a decrease in clarity of thinking at these times. However, there was no evidence of acute or chronic drug toxicity on August 1, 1966.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The role of substance abuse never resurfaced as a line of serious inquiry. Looking back at reports compiled at the time, it’s hard to understand why not.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Days after the shootings, Agent J. W. Hand of the FDA arrived in Austin under the suspicion that “such an extreme act by a hitherto sane individual might be the result of drug abuse.” The investigation was classified as a “stimulant injury investigation” and thoroughly documented Whitman’s habit and its causes, sources, and consequences.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Friends told Agent Hand that Whitman’s copious drug intake had been “frequent and obvious” over the past few months.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One, Robert Don McCrary, described Whitman’s daily strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Charles J. Whitman carried three bottles of drugs in his briefcase, these were: (1) the capsules he took to stay awake, (2) tranquilizers for his frayed nerves and (3) aspirin for the headaches he had. Although Charles J. Whitman had these drugs at all times, his most obvious use of them was when he was working against a deadline to submit a project or preparing for an examination.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Those “capsules” were typically either Dexedrine, an amphetamine, or Dexamyl, a combination of Dexedrine and the depressant amobarbital. Today, Dexedrine is highly effective in treating ADHD. In the mid-1960s, it was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2377281/&quot;&gt;widely popular&lt;/a&gt; for anything from depression to morning sickness to obesity, and was distributed throughout the military as an endurance enhancer. This last application was what Whitman sought the most. Friends alleged that he routinely used this cocktail to stay awake for multiple days and nights in a row, a pattern that he continued up to August 1. He claimed they were harmless - one friend quoted him as saying “I eat them like popcorn, they won’t hurt you.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Yet Whitman did not carry his drugs, as the FDA put it, “in the normal manner of a non-abuser.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Instead of storing them in a typical prescription bottle, he kept them in a metal tube. As for his stash at home, investigators opened the family medicine cabinet to find no fewer than eleven prescription bottles made out to Whitman by seven different doctors and filled at five pharmacies.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/johnston/prescriptions.jpg&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    The first page of three detailing the contents of the Whitman family medicine cabinet. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Image courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It was clear to Whitman’s friends that that his drugs were not entirely safe. Describing him after five days of induced insomnia, Richard Owen Clark said Whitman “was visibally [&lt;em&gt;sic&lt;/em&gt;] shaking, he could not hear the normal spoken voice, his ability to reason was impaired, his thinking was slow and you had to shake him to get his attention.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Governor’s Report was spot on when it said the drugs did more harm than good to his ability to study. As McCrary explained:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I observed that Charles Whitman’s thinking was slowed, when with the aid of drugs he had gone without sleep for periods of time. He required three to four hours to do drawings which other students completed in fifteen minutes. The project which he spent five days and nights on was done by other students in approximately three regular working days.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;When taken in doses exceeding those prescribed, Dexedrine can &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2013/021303s026lbl.pdf&quot;&gt;lead to dependence&lt;/a&gt;. By the 1960s, amphetamine abuse had reached crisis levels, and physicians knew that it was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2377281/&quot;&gt;genuinely addictive&lt;/a&gt;. It was precisely in the middle of that decade that calls began to surface for greater regulation of amphetamines in the United States; the regulation of other recreational drugs in the late 1960s and early 1970s followed in their footsteps. In 1969, the University of Texas revisited its own drug policies, eventually implementing measures to expand student access to drug treatment services. An interim report on this effort released on August 1, 1970 (presumably by coincidence), is striking for its almost nihilistic depiction of the contemporary status quo:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;However much our culture is basically drug-oriented, as exemplified by daily advertisements inducing the population to take various chemicals to wake us up, reduce our tension, put us to sleep, help us think, or improve our social prestige, it is the opinion of The University of Texas Committee on Drug Policies and Procedures … that reasonable members of an institution of higher learning cannot blindly ignore a rampant increase in drug usage such as our society is currently experiencing.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Given the relative awareness of the dangers of amphetamine abuse in 1966, it’s difficult to pin down why Whitman’s habit did not raise more of an alarm among his family and friends simply in terms of his general health. FDA interviews revealed that Whitman was quite open about his use of medication to stay awake, and most of his friends and extended family knew what kind he took. The exception may have been his father, who apparently thought he only pills he took were caffeine.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The lack of an alarm is most striking in light of Whitman’s consultation with psychiatrist Maurice D. Heatly. Whitman was referred to Heatly by a physician at the UT Student Health Center in March 1966, complaining that “something was happening to him and he didn’t seem to be himself.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Despite the fact that the referring doctor had just issued Whitman a prescription for Valium, there is no mention in Heatly’s report about substances of any kind. Given Whitman’s openness about his drug use with family, friends, and doctors, it is unlikely he would have denied it if asked.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:18&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:18&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Why Heatly didn’t bother to inquire boggles the mind. There is too much else about Heatly that also boggles the mind to touch on here; curious minds can read about him &lt;a href=&quot;/a-fitting-memorial&quot;&gt;elsewhere on this website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;One of the reasons his friends knew about the Dexedrine was that Whitman would offer it to them for free on a regular basis. While amphetamine use was common across the country in the 1960s, distributing it was not. One contemporary study indicated that the vast majority of college students got their “goofballs” from a friend - for some in Austin, Whitman was that friend. As the FDA found out, Whitman’s own source was something much more unusual:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;An effort was made to determine the source of Whitman’s drugs. He apparently had a source not only of amphetamines, but also librium and valium. This tended to indicate a drugstore as the probable Whitman drug source. By further processes of deduction it was suspected that Whitman’s source of drugs may have been the drug store in his wife’s home town of Needville, Texas. He was known to have traded at this drug store.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The Texas State Pharmacy Board, which enforces druggists sales violations in Texas for BDAC, felt that the suspected drug source should be given an immediate audit. […] This audit revealed that the drugstore in the small town (population 900) had significant, unaccountable shortages in dangerous drugs.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:20&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:20&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As Kathy’s father Raymond Leissner later told investigators, the Needville drugstore was the town’s primary gathering place, so he saw nothing unusual in the fact that Whitman would go there during each of his monthly visits. He also noted that the store owner, Hugo Frank Ley, Jr., was a close family friend, particularly to Kathy. The report then characterizes the response of Kathy’s mother, Frances Nelson-Leissner, about Whitman’s possible source of drugs as “frequently contradictory or confusing.” Technically, this is true. But this was a mother who days earlier had been robbed of her only daughter by a man she had once &lt;a href=&quot;https://catapult.co/stories/listening-to-kathy&quot;&gt;told directly&lt;/a&gt;: “By trying to completely dominate Kathy you are destroying the very things which attracted you to her in the first place.” Whatever role the Needville Pharmacy may have played in this tragedy, “contradictory” and “confusing” are perhaps the least relevant adjectives to describe Mrs. Nelson-Leissner’s situation. While it is not necessarily the FDA’s job to have sympathy for the unwitting victim of such a twisted, devastating catastrophe, the circumstances were clearly unbearable.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/johnston/needville-fullsize.jpg&quot; data-lightbox=&quot;needville&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/johnston/needville.jpg&quot; class=&quot;tall-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    The Texas Board of Pharmacy’s audit of the Needville Pharmacy, run by Leissner family friend Hugo Frank Ley, Jr., revealed a significant shortage in stock.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In the end, the FDA did not establish a definitive connection between Whitman’s substance abuse and the UT tower shootings. It left open the question of whether the prolonged sleep deprivation itself could have been a factor, but his behavior in the days before the shooting was not reminiscent of the stunted cognition his friends had described. Despite some speculation at the time that Whitman suffered from amphetamine psychosis, there is no evidence that he experienced the visual or audio hallucinations &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/14651858.CD003026.pub3/abstract&quot;&gt;characteristic of that diagnosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;C. Dean Davis, general counsel to the Texas Board of Pharmacy, was less hesitant in his conclusions. Presenting the Board’s findings to a Texas State House committee, he prefaced a similar narrative to the FDA’s:&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The following is submitted to the committee as a graphic illustration of the abuse by individuals of amphetamines and barbiturates. The example could be multiplied many times from experiences of police officers throughout the State of Texas and those connected with the Board of Pharmacy pursuant to investigations they have made concerning the use of amphetamines and barbiturates.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:21&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:21&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Indeed, Whitman’s level of substance abuse was not unique. At the end of the 1960s, Texas and states across the country found themselves up against a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2377281/&quot;&gt;fully saturated black market&lt;/a&gt; of largely unregulated pharmaceuticals with demonstrable addictive qualities and dangerous side effects for abusers. But legislators at the time were far more preoccupied with the growing prevalence of LSD.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Herein lies the lost value of including substance abuse in a broader discussion of the tower shooting. Davis and other advocates of greater regulation were adamant that amphetamine abuse was a national crisis. Whitman’s habit was part and parcel of a dangerously unstable lifestyle, one that he was increasingly unable to control towards the end of his life. It was not behavior that could be subsumed within the label, as Dr. Heatly gave him, of the “all-American boy,” except for in a sickly ironic fashion. Recognizing that Whitman was unquestionably a troubled individual, the Governor’s Report recommended that the University of Texas develop comprehensive mental health and counseling programs. That request was &lt;a href=&quot;/a-fitting-memorial&quot;&gt;followed through to the hilt&lt;/a&gt;. No recommendations were made in regards to substance abuse. If a separate recommendation for a general “health program” was meant to include narcotics, nobody seemed to notice. As noted above, the university only began to revisit its approach to drug policy in late 1969, along with the rest of the country. It seems a lost opportunity that Whitman’s case was not at least used to put a face on the epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It has taken this country a long time to come to the realization that prescription drug abuse is a crisis that cuts across class and race. Decades of normalization allowed a Caucasian, middle-upper class, male ex-marine to spend four years feeding an increasingly destabilizing drug habit and suffering virtually no social or economic consequences for it. The fact that his drug use was not directly responsible for the tower shooting does not render its existence irrelevant. Ignoring this side of Whitman’s life only helps perpetuate the myth, just now slowly beginning to die, that drug abuse is primarily a problem for minority communities and the poor. If we are to debate whether Whitman was obsessed with guns, suffering from a mental health crisis, the victim of an abominable father, an overbearing domestic abuser, an usurer, a gambler, or an “all-American boy,” then he at least does not deserve our hesitation in calling him a criminal drug addict. He may be all of these things or none of them, but perhaps the least we can do is be consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;gray bar references&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;
      &lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Institute of Pathology, letter to Dr. R Lee Clark, August 16, 1966, in the Gary L. Lavergne Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Report to the Governor, Medical Aspects, Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe,” Austin History Center.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Jerry Hall. “Tower Sniper ‘Ate Drugs Like Popcorn.’” Unidentified newspaper article, Gary M. Lavergne Papers, Box 5a, Folder 4.000, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;J.W. Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration, Bureau of Drug Abuse Control, from the files of the Texas Department of Public Safety at the Texas State Library and Archives Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;U.S. Food and Drug Administration Affidavits, from the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Inventory of medicine cabinet of Charles Whitman, Supplementary Offense Report, from the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Interim Report: Recommendations Concerning University Drug Policies and Procedures, August 1, 1970, from University Committee on Drug Policies and Procedures, UT Dean of Students Records, 1925-1986, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Dr. Maurice Dean Heatly report on Charles Whitman, March 29, 1966, from the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;S. Pearlman. (1968), DRUG USE AND EXPERIENCE IN AN URBAN COLLEGE POPULATION. &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Orthopsychiatry&lt;/em&gt;, 38: 503–514. doi: 10.1111/j.1939-0025.1968.tb00585.x&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“Whitman ‘ate drugs like candy’.” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;. March 7, 1967.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Armed Forces Institute of Pathology, letter to Dr. R Lee Clark, August 16, 1966, in the Gary L. Lavergne Papers, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Report to the Governor, Medical Aspects, Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe,” Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Jerry Hall. “Tower Sniper ‘Ate Drugs Like Popcorn.’” Unidentified newspaper article, Gary M. Lavergne Papers, Box 5a, Folder 4.000, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History; J.W. Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration, Bureau of Drug Abuse Control, from the files of the Texas Department of Public Safety at the Texas State Library and Archives Commission. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Report to the Governor, Medical Aspects, Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Report to the Governor, Medical Aspects, Charles J. Whitman Catastrophe.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;U.S. Food and Drug Administration Affidavits, from the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;U.S. Food and Drug Administration Affidavits. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Inventory of medicine cabinet of Charles Whitman, Supplementary Offense Report, from the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;U.S. Food and Drug Administration Affidavits. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;U.S. Food and Drug Administration Affidavits. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Interim Report: Recommendations Concerning University Drug Policies and Procedures, August 1, 1970, from University Committee on Drug Policies and Procedures, UT Dean of Students Records, 1925-1986, Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dr. Maurice Dean Heatly report on Charles Whitman, March 29, 1966, from the Austin Police Department files, Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:18&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:18&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;S. Pearlman. (1968), DRUG USE AND EXPERIENCE IN AN URBAN COLLEGE POPULATION. &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Orthopsychiatry&lt;/em&gt;, 38: 503–514. doi: 10.1111/j.1939-0025.1968.tb00585.x. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:20&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hand, Interim Report of Investigation, Food and Drug Administration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:20&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:21&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hall. “Tower Sniper ‘Ate Drugs Like Popcorn.’” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:21&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Whitman ‘ate drugs like candy’.” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;. March 7, 1967. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/the-little-metal-bottle</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/the-little-metal-bottle</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Texas Gun Culture and the UT Tower Shooting</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hadn’t fully comprehended that lots of people around me in Austin not only owned guns but had them close at hand and regarded themselves as free to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;J.M. Coetzee, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/96-minutes/&quot;&gt;96 Minutes&lt;/a&gt;,” &lt;cite&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;When it comes to &lt;a href=&quot;/armed-civilians-and-the-ut-tower-tragedy&quot;&gt;armed civilians&lt;/a&gt;, the UT tower shooting is a singular occurrence. To my knowledge, there are no other recent examples of a group of armed civilians, without any prior communication or planning, teaming up to fire back at a gunman in a public venue, even as the police and other officials were responding to the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In the press reports after the shooting, nobody seemed particularly fazed by the large number of armed civilians present on the UT Campus that day. To the contrary, with very few exceptions, they were treated as heroes. The few people who thought that this sequence of events was anything out of the ordinary were outsiders like J.M. Coetzee. The South African-born author was attending the UT Austin on a Fulbright Award, and thus hadn’t grown up with the Texas gun culture.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;At this point, the link between Texas and guns is treated as an immutable law of nature. The venerable magazine &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt; has published at least two special issues (April 2016 and May 1995) devoted entirely to exploring the relationship between Texans and guns, and articles like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/02/17/guns-are-a-way-of-life-in-texas/1926763/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/01/01/us/-2016-01-01-texas-open-carry-gun-law.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; that show a widespread perception of Texas as “gun friendly” are common. The day after the UT tower shooting, stories published in the United Kingdom explicitly blamed the number of guns in American society for what happened, and said that “sudden violence was familiar in America.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Though a gross oversimplification of what happened, they were right in one regard: Texas is inextricably bound up in the story of the US gun culture. In order to more fully understand what happened on the UT campus that day, we have to take a step back and examine how guns came to occupy a central place in Texas culture.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;According to a 2007 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; by the Switzerland-based Small Arms Survey, the US has a greater number of firearms per capita than any other nation, and between 35 and 50 percent of civilian-owned guns are owned by Americans.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 1966, the percentage of US households with guns was around 50%, with those in the South 22% more likely to own guns.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Those rates have fallen in the last few decades. Now, fewer than a third of Americans own guns.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Despite this downward trend, the total number of guns owned has increased.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The conventional explanation for why guns are so widespread in American culture is that ever since disembarking from the &lt;em&gt;Mayflower&lt;/em&gt;, and especially since volunteer militias fought for independence from the British, Americans have loved guns. Thus began a tradition of gun ownership that has remained intact until the present day.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Recently, this interpretation has been called into question. The historian Pamela Haag has argued that America’s current gun culture was the result of work done by early gun industrialists like Oliver Winchester and Samuel Colt. While guns have been present in America for centuries, they were primarily viewed as unexceptional objects. They were tools, necessary parts of frontier life or working on a farm. In order to expand the market for guns, though, they would have to be something more.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-advert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winchester advertisement&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    An advertisement for Winchester Rifles from 1895. In this ad and others from this period and earlier, guns were marketed as tools, text-heavy ads extolling their mechanical virtues. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Image courtesy of Wikimedia&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As it happens, the state of Texas was instrumental in Samuel Colt’s push for a wider market for his guns. William Hosley has written that Gen Sam Houston, Texas’ first senator to the United States in the 1850s, lobbied heavily for the adoption of Colt’s revolvers, saying that they should be used by every soldier on the frontier in order to prevent a “general Indian war.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Another key purchaser of Colt’s weapons was the Texas Rangers, whose members wrote about how the gun allowed them to take on groups many times their size.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These early associations with Texas would be instrumental in Colt’s later advertising campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;However, because the Civil War left the market flooded with weapons, many of the early gun industrialists nearly went out of business. Part of the problem was that guns were still viewed and marketed as tools, used by soldiers and frontiersmen.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If they were to stay in business, they would have to change how guns were viewed, from tools to objects of love. The solution came in the early 1900s, when manufacturers switched from text-heavy ads touting their guns technical virtues to more emotive, visual ads that combined nostalgia, excitement, and romance in a potent mix.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Many of these scenes would depict hunters or cowboys out West. They would also associate guns with masculinity. The text of one ad for Winchester from the 1910s said that one their rifles would “make a man of any boy,” thus marking guns as a rite of passage.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Colt would use many of the stories and images of the early Texas Rangers in marketing his weapons, linking the two in the public mind and laying the groundwork for the gun culture we see today. Guns were no longer just tools that you would use like a shovel. They were a potent symbol and a marker of identity.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;winchester-calendars&quot; data-title=&quot;Example of Winchester calendars&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-calendar-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-calendar-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;winchester-calendars&quot; data-title=&quot;Example of Winchester calendars&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-calendar-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-calendar-3-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;winchester-calendars&quot; data-title=&quot;Example of Winchester calendars&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-calendar-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/winchester-calendar-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Three examples of some of the images used on Winchester calendars used to sell rifles. The images were richly colored and presented a far more emotive emotive image of guns that made them items of symbolic significance, not just tools. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Images courtesy of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://centerofthewest.org&quot;&gt;Buffalo Bill Center of the West&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Popular media would also play a key role in fostering gun culture with the production of Westerns. Between 1950 and 1961, Hollywood produced over 600 films set between 1866 and 1890, the vast majority of them westerns. By 1959, there were 30 western TV shows running in primetime, and they made up 8 of the top 10 shows. And book publishers sold an average of 35 million paperback westerns a year.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:12&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:12&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The final piece of the puzzle when considering Texas gun culture is hunting. After World War II, many soldiers returned home with a new interest in firearms. They joined the National Rifle Association, which was then mostly concerned with marksmanship. However, the returning soldiers were more interested in hunting, and consequently the NRA’s magazine, &lt;em&gt;American Rifleman&lt;/em&gt;, switched its coverage to emphasize hunting at the expense of target shooting.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:13&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:13&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This is borne out by polling data from the 1960s, which shows that over 80% of the weapons owned were shotguns or rifles, implying that they were primarily used for hunting.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:14&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:14&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The survey didn’t examine numbers by state, but it’s safe to assume that Texas followed this trend closely, given the importance of firearms in rural life. In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/great-guns/&quot;&gt;reflecting back&lt;/a&gt; on his collection of firearms, the writer John Graves emphasized how central guns were to everyday life, from keeping the land clear of varmints to fending off rattlesnakes. It also was a way of bonding with his father. The journalist Robert Draper noted something similar in his piece on a group of hunters in East Texas. Hunting wasn’t just for sport or sustenance. It was a bonding ritual.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:15&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:15&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep this aspect of bonding in mind. Charles Whitman grew up in Florida, which also has a history of gun ownership, where his father taught him how to use firearms from an early age. It was one of the ways the two men related to each other, and it was one of the few things about his son that the elder Whitman praised unreservedly.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:16&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:16&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; From an early age, Whitman had hunting in his blood, as did many of those who shot back at him.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;One particular article, titled “Arsenal Ordinary in Texas,” published by &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt; on August 4, 1966, is useful for illustrating the ubiquity and banality of guns in Texas. It examined the arsenal that Charles Whitman took with him to the top of the tower. When Austin police officials went through the footlocker Whitman dragged up there with him they found four rifles, two shotguns, and five pistols, along with a substantial stockpile of ammunition and other supplies. To those who did not grow up in a gun culture, this collection sounds excessive. However, several sportsmen said afterwards that arsenals this size and even larger were not uncommon in Texas households. The secretary of the Texas Senate himself reported owning six rifles, three shotguns, and a pistol.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:17&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:17&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;sor-report&quot; data-title=&quot;SOR report listing contents of Whitman’s trunk (page 1)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/sor-report-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/sor-report-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;sor-report&quot; data-title=&quot;SOR report listing contents of Whitman’s trunk (page 2)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/sor-report-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/sor-report-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;sor-report&quot; data-title=&quot;SOR report listing contents of Whitman’s trunk (page 3)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/sor-report-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/sor-report-3-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;sor-report&quot; data-title=&quot;Photo of Whitman’s stockpile&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/contents-of-whitmans-trunk-ahc.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/contents-of-whitmans-trunk-ahc-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    The Austin Police Department recorded the contents of Whitman&#39;s trunk that he brought with him to the top of the tower. His stockpile demonstrated that he was planning on holding out for a substantial period of time, but area sportsmen didn&#39;t regard his collection as anything out of the ordinary. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Images courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The article also listed a few statistics on the number of weapons in Texas at the time. In the first seven months of 1966, the Department of Public Safety said that they had reported sales of 175,768 pistols. The previous year, the state had issued 571,058 regular resident hunting licenses, with an estimated 160,000 license exemptions issued to people under 17, over 65, or who wished to hunt on their own land. The total population in Texas at the time was about 10.38 million.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;There is one further thing that this article tells us. It states that at the time, private citizens were not allowed to carry pistols. However, Texas law was mute on the subject of rifles and Texas sportsmen were among the most vocal opponents of any sort of gun control legislation. Immediately after the shooting, there was general outcry for greater gun control, but it was staunchly opposed by Earle Cabell, a representative from Dallas, and many others, on the grounds that new gun laws wouldn’t have stopped Whitman and would unduly punish sportsmen.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:18&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:18&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the end, the legislation would stall until after the assassinations of Robert F. Kennedy and Martin Luther King, Jr. in 1968.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;To be clear, many people still viewed the rifle as a tool, a necessary part of life on the ranch or the farm. But in many ways, it was like a shootout in an old western, with people playing the roles modeled for them by cowboys and Texas Rangers. Could this have happened anywhere else? Some academics have hypothesized on the increased level of violence in southern society, especially in vigilante or “defensive” situations.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:19&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:19&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There’s little empirical evidence to back this up, so the question is left open. Was there something peculiarly American, or southern, or Texan about dozens of armed civilians appearing on a public university campus? Is this sort of violence inevitable in a society that attaches mythical status to guns, produces media saturated with gun violence, and sees firearms as part of its history from its earliest days? I won’t pretend to know the answer. All I can do is echo Allen Crum’s statement, which he gave to &lt;em&gt;American Rifleman&lt;/em&gt; in 1966: “The right of the private citizen to bear arms was never more graphically demonstrated than on the University of Texas Campus Aug. 1, 1966.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Story of Slayings in World Headlines,” &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;, August 3, 1966. Found in “Tower Sniper Vertical Files,” Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Small Arms Survey, and Graduate Institute of International Studies, &lt;em&gt;Small Arms Survey 2007: Guns and the City&lt;/em&gt;, (Cambridge; New York: Cambridge University Press, 2007), accessed April 24, 2016: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html&quot;&gt;http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/publications/by-type/yearbook/small-arms-survey-2007.html&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;James D. Wright and Linda L. Marston, “The Ownership of the Means of Destruction: Weapons in the United States,” &lt;em&gt;Social Problems&lt;/em&gt; 23 (1975), 93, 96. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bindu Kalesan, Marcos D Villarreal, Katherine M Keyes and Sandro Galea, “Gun Ownership and Social Gun Culture,” &lt;em&gt;Injury Prevention&lt;/em&gt;, June 29, 2015, accessed April 24, 2016, doi:10.1136/injuryprev-2015-041586. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;William J. Krouse and Library of Congress, Congressional Research Service, &lt;em&gt;Gun control legislation in the 112th Congress&lt;/em&gt;, Washington D.C.: Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress (2012), accessed April 24, 2016: &lt;a href=&quot;https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/RL32842.pdf&quot;&gt;https://fas.org/sgp/crs/misc/RL32842.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kathryn Kahler, “Americans Love Their Guns but Fear Violence,” in &lt;em&gt;Guns in America: A Reader&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jan E Dizard, Robert Merrill Muth, and Stephen P Andrews, Jr., 158-161. (New York: New York University Press, 1999), 159. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;William Hosley, “Guns, Gun Culture, and the Peddling of Dreams,” in &lt;em&gt;Guns in America: A Reader&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jan E Dizard, Robert Merrill Muth, and Stephen P Andrews, Jr., 47-85, (New York: New York University Press, 1999), 65-67. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;James Donovan, “Two Sams and Their Six-Shooter,” &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt;, March 22, 2016, accessed April 17, 2016, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/the-culture/two-sams-and-their-six-shooter/&quot;&gt;http://www.texasmonthly.com/the-culture/two-sams-and-their-six-shooter/&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Haag, &lt;em&gt;The Gunning of America: Business and the Making of the American Gun Culture&lt;/em&gt;, (Basic Books: New York), 255. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Haag, &lt;em&gt;The Gunning of America&lt;/em&gt;, 251. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Haag, &lt;em&gt;The Gunning of America&lt;/em&gt;, 333. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:12&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;David Courtwright, “The Cowboy Subculture,” in &lt;em&gt;Guns in America: A Reader&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jan E Dizard, Robert Merrill Muth, and Stephen P Andrews, Jr., 86-104, (New York: New York University Press,1999), 98. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:12&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:13&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Robert J. Spitzer, &lt;em&gt;The Politics of Gun Control&lt;/em&gt;, 5th ed. (Boulder, CO: Paradigm Publishers 2012) 90. It was also around this time that the NRA became more heavily invested in shaping legislation, but that history is far too complex to tackle here. Several works have been written on the topic. A good place to start for recent NRA lobbying efforts against gun control legislation is Robert Draper’s 2013 piece for the &lt;em&gt;New York Times’ Magazine&lt;/em&gt; titled “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/12/15/magazine/inside-the-power-of-the-nra.html&quot;&gt;Inside the Power of the N.R.A.&lt;/a&gt;” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:13&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:14&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Adam Walinsky, “The Crisis of Public Order,” in &lt;em&gt;Guns in America: A Reader&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jan E Dizard, Robert Merrill Muth, and Stephen P Andrews, Jr., 291-303, (New York: New York University Press,1999), 299. Hard data on gun ownership rates is notoriously scarce and thus a little bit of extrapolation is usually necessary. For instance, when people asked about gun ownership rates for this poll, they didn’t ask what the guns were used for. We can only infer that, because handguns are usually purchased for self-defense, that the majority of the people in the ‘60s were using their firearms for hunting or other sporting activities, like target shooting. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:14&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:15&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Robert Draper, email message to author, March 24, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:15&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:16&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gary Lavergne, &lt;em&gt;A Sniper in the Tower: The Charles Whitman Murders&lt;/em&gt; (Denton, Tex: University of North Texas Press, 1997) 5. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:16&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:17&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Paul Recer, “Arsenal Ordinary in Texas,” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, August 4, 1966, Found in “Tower Sniper Vertical Files,” Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:17&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:18&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cabell Raps Gun Owners Restrictions, &lt;em&gt;Dallas Times Herald&lt;/em&gt;, August 3, 1966, Found in “Tower Sniper Vertical Files,” Dolph Briscoe Center for American History. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:18&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:19&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Christopher G. Ellison, “Southern Culture and Firearms Ownership,” &lt;em&gt;Social Science Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; 72 (1991). (Austin: University of Texas Press): 267-83 and Courtwright, “The Cowboy Subculture.” &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:19&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/texas-gun-culture-and-the-ut-tower-shooting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/texas-gun-culture-and-the-ut-tower-shooting</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Armed Civilians and the UT Tower Tragedy</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;white bar&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-12 col-md-10 col-md-offset-1 col-lg-8 col-lg-offset-2 post-content&quot;&gt;

      &lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It seemed like every other guy had a rifle. There was a sort of cowboy atmosphere, this “Let’s get him” spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;Ann Major, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/96-minutes/&quot;&gt;96 Minutes&lt;/a&gt;,” &lt;cite&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;On August 1, 2016, Texas Senate Bill 11 will go into effect, allowing license holders to carry concealed weapons throughout university campuses. Though private universities will have the option to opt-out, state schools will not. The legislation has been particularly contentious on the campus of the University of Texas at Austin, where &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/13/us/gun-advocates-demonstrate-outside-university-of-texas-campus.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;mock shootings&lt;/a&gt; have played out against a backdrop of &lt;a href=&quot;http://kut.org/post/ut-groups-protest-ahead-first-meeting-campus-carry-policy&quot;&gt;resistance&lt;/a&gt; from students, faculty, staff, and some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2015/oct/12/texas-guns-prompts-debate-over-dildos&quot;&gt;wonderfully&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chron.com/about/article/ut-austin-texas-dildos-mass-farting-fart-protest-6694231.php&quot;&gt;absurdist&lt;/a&gt; protests.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;August 1st will also mark the 50th anniversary since the UT tower shooting, commonly referred to as the first mass school shooting in US history.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Texas state government hasn’t elaborated on why they chose this particular date and not another, but we should not view it as a coincidence. Armed civilians are a crucial part of the story, one that’s been politicized by both gun rights and gun control advocates, and all of this takes place against the backdrop of a state that is in many ways the heartland of &lt;a href=&quot;/texas-gun-culture-and-the-ut-tower-shooting&quot;&gt;gun culture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;When Whitman began shooting, the Austin Police Department was ill-equipped for the situation. They mostly possessed only their service revolvers and shotguns, weapons that were useless when it came to long distances. If they did possess a rifle, it was because it was a personal weapon.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The officers weren’t alone, though. Once bystanders realized what was going on, many ran to retrieve their own firearms and fired back at the tower. In a few instances, police officers drove people in their squad cars to purchase ammunition or to pick up rifles. Some people asked police what to do if they had a shot at the sniper. The police said that they should shoot to kill.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/bullet-holes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photos of bullet holes&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Gun marks on the side of the UT tower. Most of these marks have since been plastered over. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Image courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;video-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/267tQEV&quot; id=&quot;first-video-link&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/first-video-poster.jpg&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;play-button&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;first-video-container&quot; style=&quot;display: none&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/interface/loader.svg&quot; class=&quot;loader&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    $(&#39;#first-video-link&#39;).on(&#39;click&#39;, function(e) {
        e.preventDefault();
        $(&#39;#first-video-link&#39;).hide();
        $(&#39;#first-video-container&#39;).show();
        $.get(&#39;/video/mcquistion-first-video.html&#39;, function(data) {
          $(&#39;#first-video-container&#39;).html(data);
          });
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Local news cameras recorded some of the firefight. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Video clip courtesy of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/267tQEV&quot;&gt;Texas Archive of the Moving Image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It was a surreal scene. Bill Helmer, who was a student at UT at the time, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/the-madman-on-the-tower/&quot;&gt;recounted his experience&lt;/a&gt; on campus that day in &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt;. When he first noticed people shooting back at the tower, he thought, “Just what we need – a bunch of loonies lobbing bullets all over the place, killing even more people.” He recalled seeing a man in full camo scouting out the best position from which to fire back at the tower, and claims that his friends saw a good ol’ boy with a rifle burst into the San Jacinto Cafe southeast of campus, grab a six pack of beer, and rush out.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;But then he realized that “as the ground fire increased, the shots from the tower came less often.” The return fire was limiting the amount of damage Whitman was able to do by keeping him pinned down and robbing him of the time he wanted to pick his targets. This realization was widely shared.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It’s undeniable that many civilians on campus that day displayed tremendous bravery, stepping up when the police couldn’t.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But their presence was not unproblematic. The truth, as always, is more complicated than that of good guys battling a bad guy.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;In a statement given in November 1966 to &lt;em&gt;American Rifleman&lt;/em&gt;, a commercial publication of the National Rifle Association, Allen Crum recounts his actions and how he ended up with officers at the top of the tower. At the time, Crum was recently retired from the US Air Force and was working as a floor manager at the University Co-op, located across the street from the UT campus. After Whitman started shooting, Crum offered his help and, armed with a rifle given to him by an officer, he and a few other members of the APD made their way to the tower observation deck.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;video-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1OeyhrY&quot; id=&quot;second-video-link&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/second-video-poster.jpg&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;play-button&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;second-video-container&quot; style=&quot;display: none&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/interface/loader.svg&quot; class=&quot;loader&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    $(&#39;#second-video-link&#39;).on(&#39;click&#39;, function(e) {
      e.preventDefault();
      $(&#39;#second-video-link&#39;).hide();
      $(&#39;#second-video-container&#39;).show();
      $.get(&#39;/video/mcquistion-second-video.html&#39;, function(data) {
        $(&#39;#second-video-container&#39;).html(data);
        });
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Allen Crum talks about his experience storming the tower with police officers on the local news. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Video clip courtesy of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/1OeyhrY&quot;&gt;Texas Archive of the Moving Image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Crum is unambiguous on the role that armed civilians played in the shooting at this point. “The ground fire was really a Godsend to us,” he wrote, “as it got Whitman pinned down in one spot … We had no means of communication to stop it, but I don’t think that we would have stopped it.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;As the only civilian in the group that stormed the tower observation deck, Crum became one of the heroes of the UT tower tragedy. He was widely fêted afterwards, receiving a Bravery Award from the Texas Law Enforcement Association&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the Respect for Law Award from Optimist International, an international service organization that focuses on youth.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Statement (page 1)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Statement (page 2)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Statement (page 3)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-3-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Statement (page 4)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-4-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Allen Crum’s statement, given to the police immediately after the shooting. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Images courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 1)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 2)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 3)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-3-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 4)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-4-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 5)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-5.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-5-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 6)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-6.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-6-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 7)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-7.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-7-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 8)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-8.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-8-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 9)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-9.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-9-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 10)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-10.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-10-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 11)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-11.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-11-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 12)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-12.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-12-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 13)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-13.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-13-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;crum-ar&quot; data-title=&quot;Allen Crum’s Interview with &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;American Rifleman&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; (page 14)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-14.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/crum-ar-14-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Allen Crum also gave a description of his experience to American Rifleman, a publication of the National Rifle Association. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt; Images courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;However, APD Officer Houston McCoy’s account complicates this story. McCoy also stormed the tower – though he acted independently of Crum – and he, along with Officer Ramiro Martinez, are credited with killing Whitman. In 1985, McCoy sent Bill Helmer, at this point a reporter for &lt;em&gt;Playboy&lt;/em&gt;, his own version of events. After McCoy made his way into the tower, he joined with Officer Jerry Day to go up to the observation deck. At this point, and unknown to McCoy, Allen Crum and Officer Martinez were already there. When McCoy heard someone coming down the stairs to enter the room where McCoy was holed up, he prepared to fire.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;“I kept hearing noise in the room above and Jerry Day sensing that I was about to shoot the first thing that showed from up there told me that Officer Ramiro Martinez and a civilian were up there. It is a good thing the civilian did not start down the stairs before I learned of him being there.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;A very good thing, because Crum, a civilian at the top of the tower carrying a rifle, would have exactly matched the profile of the shooter McCoy was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Official Report (page 1)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Official Report (page 2)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Houston McCoy’s official report, written immediately after the shooting. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Images courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;image-gallery image-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (Cover Letter)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-intro2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-intro2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 1)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-1-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 2)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-2-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 3)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-3-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 4)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-4-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 5)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-5.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-5-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 6)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-6.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-6-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 7)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-7.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-7-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 8)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-8.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-8-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 9)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-9.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-9-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image col-xs-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a data-lightbox=&quot;mccoy-helmer&quot; data-title=&quot;Houston McCoy’s Letter to Bill Helmer (page 10)&quot; href=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-10.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/mccoy-helmer-10-thumb.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Several years later, Houston McCoy described his experience storming the tower and killing Charles Whitman to Bill Helmer, a reporter and fellow survivor of the UT tower shooting. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Images courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.austintexas.gov/ahc/about-us&quot;&gt;Austin History Center, Austin Public Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;McCoy goes on to describe the ground fire that peppered the tower and narrowly missed them while he, Crum, and the other officers got into position on the observation deck. In a press conference after the shooting, Texas Governor &lt;a href=&quot;/texas-gun-culture-and-the-ut-tower-shooting&quot;&gt;John Connally said&lt;/a&gt; that the ground fire impeded the progress of officers to the top of the tower. After McCoy and Martinez killed Whitman, they then had no effective way of telling those on the ground to stop firing. Crum waved a white flag, but even after that, sporadic ground fire continued. McCoy said that at least one TV report had shown Crum waving the flag and claimed that it was the shooter trying to give up.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; No doubt the same thought occurred to many of those firing at the tower.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;video-block&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/28XSQqA&quot; id=&quot;third-video-link&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/mcquistion/third-video-poster.jpg&quot; class=&quot;video-poster&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;play-button&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;third-video-container&quot; style=&quot;display: none&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/interface/loader.svg&quot; class=&quot;loader&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    $(&#39;#third-video-link&#39;).on(&#39;click&#39;, function(e) {
      e.preventDefault();
      $(&#39;#third-video-link&#39;).hide();
      $(&#39;#third-video-container&#39;).show();
      $.get(&#39;/video/mcquistion-third-video.html&#39;, function(data) {
        $(&#39;#third-video-container&#39;).html(data);
      });
    });
  &lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Texas Governor John Connally, while defending his Police Department, said that ground fire from civilians actually impeded the progress of officers to the top of the tower. &lt;span class=&quot;credit&quot;&gt;Video clip provided courtesy of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/28XSQqA&quot;&gt;Texas Archive of the Moving Image&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;By juxtaposing these two accounts, we’re able to get a more complete picture of the role armed citizens played in the UT tower shootings. The ground fire did pin down Whitman, most likely keeping him from killing more people. However, it’s not difficult to see how the actions of several armed, independent citizens could have resulted in further tragedy, and that it was only through fortuitous circumstance that they didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Armed civilians had one final effect on what happened that day. Claire Wilson was eight months pregnant when Whitman shot her and her boyfriend as they walked across the upper terrace of the South Mall. Her boyfriend, Thomas Eckman, died instantly, but Claire was only wounded. As she lay in the brutal sun, injured and unable to move, chaos engulfed the UT campus. It would be more than an hour before a woman and three young men would be able to run out and carry her to safety.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Years later, in 2015, Claire Wilson, now Claire James, testified before the Texas State Senate Affairs Committee. The Committee was considering bills that would increase the number of weapons permitted on college campuses. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chron.com/about/article/Whitman-victim-testifies-against-open-carry-6077967.php&quot;&gt;In her testimony&lt;/a&gt;, James said that the armed citizens who were firing back at Whitman had kept emergency personnel from reaching her and her boyfriend sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is a bit of a fraught claim. Though commonly referred to as the first mass school shooting, it’s probably more accurate to say that it was the first mass school shooting broadcast live (or very close to it) into people’s homes. There have been numerous other instances of mass violence, many of them inside of public schools. For more information on the history of public violence in the United States, see &lt;a href=&quot;/a-brief-history-of-mass-shootings&quot;&gt;Maria’s essay&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Gary Lavergne, &lt;em&gt;A Sniper in the Tower: The Charles Whitman Murders&lt;/em&gt; (Denton, Tex: University of North Texas Press, 1997). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Houston McCoy, “Record from Houston McCoy,” Archival document, AR.2000.002, Box 12, Folder 16. Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And the police definitely couldn’t, though due to lack of preparation rather than incompetence. Gary Lavergne’s &lt;em&gt;Sniper in the Tower&lt;/em&gt; does a good job of portraying the confusion and panic that gripped campus that day, and &lt;a href=&quot;/policing&quot;&gt;Justin’s essay&lt;/a&gt; delves further into just how unprepared the police department was for this kind of situation and what measures the adopted afterwards. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Allen Crum, “Text for Article in &lt;em&gt;American Rifleman&lt;/em&gt;.” Archival document, n.d. AR.2000.002, Box 12, Folder 12. Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Bravery Awards” &lt;em&gt;The Austin American&lt;/em&gt;, Sept 18, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Optimists to Honor Crum for his Deed,” &lt;em&gt;The Austin Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, Aug 22, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Houston McCoy, “Record from Houston McCoy,” Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Houston McCoy, “Record from Houston McCoy,“ Austin History Center. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Pamela Colloff, “The Reckoning,” &lt;em&gt;Texas Monthly&lt;/em&gt;, April 2016, 95-97. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://behindthetower.org/armed-civilians-and-the-ut-tower-tragedy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://behindthetower.org/armed-civilians-and-the-ut-tower-tragedy</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
